<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="user_manual"><info><title>User guide</title></info>			
	<section xml:id="Create_job"><info><title>Create a job</title></info>
		<para>
			A job is the entity that will be submitted to the ProActive Scheduler. As it has been explained in the <xref linkend="what_is_job"/>, it is possible to create more than one type of job. A job can be created using an XML descriptor or the provided ProActive Scheduler Java API or also with a simple flat file.
		</para>
		<section xml:id="Create_job_xml"><info><title>Job XML descriptor</title></info>
			<para>
			The  Job  XML descriptor is created 
			following the 
			<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://proactive.inria.fr/schemas/jobdescriptor/1.0/schedulerjob.xsd">
			descriptor XSD schema</uri>
			</para>
			<para>
				Several parameters can be set for a job:
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>name</emphasis> - name of the job.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>projectName</emphasis> (optional) - name of the project. 
							This information provide a way to gather different jobs.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>priority</emphasis> (optional - normal by default) - scheduling priority level of the job. 
							A user can only set the priority of his jobs and can only use the values 'lowest', 'low', or 'normal'. 
							There are two higher priority levels
							'high' and 'highest' which can be only set by the administrator. 
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>cancelJobOnError</emphasis> (optional - false by default) - defines whether 
							the job must continue when a user exception or
							error occurs during the job process.
							This property can also be defined in each task.
							If the value of this property is defined at the job level, each cancelJobOnError property of each task
							will have this value as the default one (excepted if this property has been set at the task level). 
							'True' implies for the job to immediately stop every remaining running tasks if an error occurs in one of
							the tasks. It is useful when there is no need to go further after a task failure.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>restartTaskOnError</emphasis> (optional - anywhere by default) - defines whether tasks that have to be restarted 
							will restart on an other resource.
							Defining this property will set the restartTaskOnError property of each task
							to this value as the default one (excepted if this property has been set at the task level). 
							Possible values are 'anywhere' or 'elsewhere' meaning respectively
							that the concerned task will be restart on any available resources or especially on a different one.
							A task can be restarted when an exception occurred (Java Task) or an error code is returned (Native Task).
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>nbMaxOfExecution</emphasis> (optional - 1 by default) - defines how many times tasks are allowed to be restarted.
							Defining this property will set the nbMaxOfExecution property of each task to this value as the default one
							(excepted if this property has been set at the task level).
							The value has to be a non-negative and non-null integer.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>logFile</emphasis> (optional) - path of a log file.
							Set it if you want to save the job generated logs (STDOUT and STDERR) in a file.
							<emphasis>As this file is created and filled by the scheduler server, the path must be
							also reachable from the scheduler server (not only from the client).</emphasis>
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>description</emphasis> (optional) - human readable description of the job.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>variables</emphasis> (optional) - variables which can be reused throughout the descriptor file.
							Inside this tag, each variable can be reused (even in another following variable definition)
							by using the syntax ${name_of_variable}.
							Note that you can also refer to variables defined in the JVM properties. 
							For instance, if the JVM that starts the Job parser (JobFactory)
							has been started with the option -Dtoto=helloWorld, the variable ${toto} in the XML descriptor file would have 'helloWorld' as value.
							This way is not commonly used but can be very useful to manage your relative path.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>genericInformation</emphasis> (optional) - defines some information inside your job.
							These information can be read by the policy of the Scheduler and can be used
							to modify the scheduling behavior. As an example, the administrator can set the policy
							to be influenced by this information.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>JobClasspath</emphasis> (optional) - equivalent to the Java classpath.
							All classes in this path can be loaded by
							java tasks contained in this job. The jobClasspath can either contain class directories or jar files.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
				<warning><para> The jobClasspath mechanism relies on the file transfer. The size of the jobClasspath
				files therefore has an impact on performances, especially on the time spent on submitting jobs.</para></warning> 

			<para>Here is an example of a job descriptor:</para>

			<programlisting language="xml"><textobject><textdata fileref="scheduler/xml/job.xml"/></textobject></programlisting>
			
			<para>This example does not contain the job type definition. We detail the job type definition in the next sections.</para>
			<para>
				To create a ProActive Job, please refer to <xref linkend="Create_ProActive_job_xml" />. To create a Taskflow Job, please refer to <xref linkend="Create_TaskFlow_job_xml" />.
			</para>
		</section>
			
		<section xml:id="Create_TaskFlow_job_xml"><info><title>Create a Task Flow job using an XML descriptor</title></info>
			<para>
				A Task Flow job is a job that can
				contain one or several task(s) with needed dependencies.
				To specify that a job is a Task Flow Job, you have to add the 'taskFlow' tag.
				The previous would therefore be written as follows:
			</para>
			<programlisting language="xml"><textobject><textdata fileref="scheduler/xml/taskFlow_job.xml" /></textobject></programlisting>
			<para>
				The creation and addition of tasks is described in <xref linkend="Create_add_task" />.
			</para>
		</section>
		
		<section xml:id="Create_ProActive_job_xml"><info><title>Create a ProActive job using an XML descriptor</title></info>
			<para>
				To specify that a job is a ProActive job, you just have to add a 'proActive' tag into it.
				The previous example would look like that:
			</para>
			<programlisting language="xml"><textobject><textdata fileref="scheduler/xml/ProActive_job.xml" /></textobject></programlisting>
			<para>
				The creation and addition of tasks is described in <xref linkend="Create_add_task" />.
			</para>
		</section>
		
		<section xml:id="Create_TaskFlow_job_java"><info><title>Create a Task Flow job using the Java API</title></info>
			<para>
				To make a new instance of a TaskFlow job, you have to create a new 
				<code>TaskFlowJob</code> object:
			</para>
			<programlisting language="java"> <textobject><textdata fileref="automatic_snippets/task_flow_job_creation.snip" /></textobject></programlisting>
		</section>
	

		<section xml:id="Create_ProActive_job_java"><info><title>Create a ProActive job using the Java API</title></info>
			<para>
				To make a new instance of a ProActive job, you have to create a new 
				<code>ProActiveJob</code> object:
			</para>
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[ ProActiveJob job = new ProActiveJob();]]></programlisting>
  		</section>
		
		<section xml:id="Parameters_job_java"><info><title>Set job parameters using the Java API</title></info>
			<para>
				Job parameters created through the Java API are identical to those created through
				XML files (see <xref linkend="Create_job_xml"/>).
				The example below creates a TaskFlow job (works also with ProActive jobs) using the Java Scheduler API and sets some parameters for the job:
			</para>
<!--			<programlisting language="java"><textobject><textdata fileref="automatic_snippets/taskflow_params.snip"/></textobject></programlisting>-->
			<programlisting language="java">
TaskFlowJob job = new TaskFlowJob();
job.setName("job name");
job.setPriority(JobPriority.NORMAL);
job.setCancelJobOnError(false);
job.setLogFile("path/to/a/log/file.log");
job.setDescription("Job description");
job.addGenericInformation("var1","val1");
job.addGenericInformation("var2","val2");
JobEnvironment je = new JobEnvironment();
je.setJobClasspath(new String[]{"/path/to/my/classes/","/path/to/my/jarfile.jar"}); 
job.setEnv(je);
			</programlisting>
			<para>
				To create and add tasks to your job, please refer to <xref linkend="Create_add_task"/>.
			</para>
		</section>
		
		<section xml:id="flat_file_job"><info><title>Create a job in a simple flat file</title></info>
			<para> ProActive Scheduler provides a way to define a job with a simple plain text file. This method is simpler than an XML file but presents less features.
			</para>
			<para>
			If you just need to launch a set of native tasks in parallel, <emphasis>without dependancies between tasks</emphasis>, you can create a simple text file
			and write a list of native commands to submit:
			</para>
			<programlisting language="xml">
# a flat text file containing native commands to launch
# one command per line
#
# One rule to know:
# command paths must be absolute paths

/path/to/my/exec/myCmd.sh 1
/path/to/my/exec/myCmd.sh 2
/path/to/my/exec/myCmd.sh 3
/path/to/my/exec/myCmd.sh 4
			</programlisting>
			<para>
			This file represents a job made of 4 native tasks, i.e. 4 native commands to launch. Each line beginning with a '#' is a comment, and is not taken into account.
			You have to put one native command per line, and commands must be absolute paths. Contrary to a job definition in XML, you cannot specify any dependencies between tasks.
			This job definition is useful for embarrassingly parallel jobs. Many features of job are not available at creation time, but can be specified at submission time: log file, job name, and selection scripts.
			</para>
			<para>
			To see how to submit this kind of job descriptor, see <xref linkend="Submit_a_job_sh" />.
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section xml:id="Create_add_task"><info><title>Create and add a task to a job</title></info>
		<para>
			As it has been said, it is possible to create 3 types of tasks. Native and
			Java tasks can be add to TaskFlow Job, and one ProActive Task to one ProActive Job.
		</para>
		<section xml:id="Create_java_task"><info><title>Create and add a Java task</title></info>
			<para>
				<emphasis>Note</emphasis> : A java task can only be added to a TaskFlow Job.
			</para>
			<para>
				To learn how to create a TaskFlow job,
				pleas refer to <xref linkend="Create_TaskFlow_job_xml"/> or <xref linkend="Create_TaskFlow_job_java"/>.
				Once your TaskFlow job created, you can add as many Java tasks as needed to perform an application.
			</para>
			<section xml:id="define_executable_java"><info><title>Define your own Java executable</title></info>
				<para>
					You can create your own java executable by implementing scheduler executable interfaces.
					In this sens, 'executable' means the executed process (that is a Java class in this case).
					Here is an example on how to create your own Java executable:
				</para>
				<programlisting language="java">
public class WaitAndPrint extends JavaExecutable {

	@Override
	public Serializable execute(TaskResult... results) throws Throwable {
		String message;

		try {
			System.err.println("Démarrage de la tache WaitAndPrint");
			System.out.println("Parameters are : ");

			for (TaskResult tRes : results) {
				if (tRes.hadException()) {
					System.out.println("\t " + tRes.getTaskId() + " : " + tRes.getException().getMessage());
				} else {
					System.out.println("\t " + tRes.getTaskId() + ": " + tRes.value());
				}
			}

			message = URIBuilder.getLocalAddress().toString();
			Thread.sleep(10000);

		} catch (Exception e) {
			message = "crashed";
			e.printStackTrace();
		}

		System.out.println("Task terminated");

		return (message + "\t slept for 10 sec");
	}
}
				</programlisting>
				<para>
					This executable will print an initial message, then check if there are results from previous tasks
					and if so, print the value of these "parameters". It will then return a message
					containing what the task did. The return value will be store in the job result.
				</para>
				<para>
					It is also possible to get a list of arguments that you can give to the executable at its start by
					overriding the init method on a Java executable. The way to give arguments to the task will be explain
					later.
					Let's see how you can give a foo, a bar and a test argument to the previous example:
					<programlisting language="java">
private boolean foo;
private int bar;
private String test;

@Override
public void init(Map&lt;String, Object&gt; args) {
	foo = (Boolean)args.get("foo");
	bar = (Integer)args.get("bar");
	test = args.get("test");
}
					</programlisting>
				</para>
				<para>
					The previous code is given as an example. The default behavior of the init() method is to associate declared
					Java variables to their value, assuming that the variable names given in arguments (in the map) are the same as the Java declared ones.
					Thus, The given code behaves exactly like the following code:
					<programlisting language="java">
private boolean foo;
private int bar;
private String test;

@Override
public void init(Map&lt;String, Object&gt; args) {
	super.init(args);
}
					</programlisting>
				</para>
				<para>
					To sum up, create an executable is just extending the <code>JavaExecutable</code> abstract class, and filling
					the execute method. The given <code>TaskResult... results</code> argument enables to get the results from
					previous dependent tasks that have finished their execution.
				</para>
				<para>
					As shown in the following lines, the given array of TaskResults (<emphasis>results</emphasis>)
					will be an array of two results (TaskResult 2 and 3) in this order
					if the dependences of Task 5 is Task 2 and Task 3 in this order.
					Therefore you can use them to perform Task 5 process.
					<programlisting language="java">
@Override
public Serializable execute(TaskResult... results) throws Throwable {
	//TaskResult
	tResult2 = results[0];
	//TaskResult
	tResult3 = results[1];
}
					</programlisting>
				</para>
				<para>
					Finally, overriding the <code>init()</code> method can be useful if you want to retrieve personal arguments or do some
					operations before starting the real execution of the task.
				</para>
			</section>
			
			<section xml:id="Create_java_task_xml"><info><title>Create and add a Java task using an XML descriptor</title></info>
					<para>
						The task is the entity that will be scheduled by ProActive Scheduler.
						As it has been explained in <xref linkend="what_is_task"/>,
						it's possible to create and add Java tasks to your TaskFlow Job.
						A Java task can either be created using an XML descriptor or using the provided ProActive Scheduler Java API.
						This section deals with the creation of a task and its addition to a job.
					</para>
				<para>
					Take a look at the following example to understand the syntax of a task:
				</para>
				<programlisting language="xml"><textobject><textdata fileref="scheduler/xml/java_task_simple.xml"/></textobject></programlisting>
				<para>
					The Java task is composed of a 'javaExecutable' tag which specifies the Java executable class to be used.
					A set of parameters can also be defined as it has been done for this example. These parameters will be
					available into the <code>Map</code> of the <code>init(Map)</code> method into your <code>JavaExecutable</code>.
					This example also shows the definition of two tasks with dependencies. We can easily see that 'task 2' depends on
					'task 1'. So 'task 2' will be executed only once 'task 1' has finished.
					To put these two tasks inside your TaskFlow job, just put it between the 'taskFlow' tags.
					Here is a complete ready-to-be-scheduled TaskFlow job:
				</para>
				<programlisting language="xml"><textobject><textdata fileref="scheduler/xml/taskFlow_job_complete.xml"/></textobject></programlisting>
				<para>
					It is obviously possible to mix Java and Native task inside a taskFlow Job.
					Some other parameters and options can be set into a Java task. The two following examples expose some of them:
				</para>
				<programlisting language="xml"><textobject><textdata fileref="scheduler/xml/java_task_script.xml"/></textobject></programlisting>
				<programlisting language="xml"><textobject><textdata fileref="scheduler/xml/java_task_fork.xml"/></textobject></programlisting>
				<para>
					To have an exhaustive list of available options and theirs functions, please refer to
					the task explanation section (see <xref linkend="Create_task_explanation"/>).
				</para>
			</section>
			<section xml:id="Create_java_task_java"><info><title>Create and add a Java task using the Java API</title></info>
				<para>
					To <emphasis>create a Java task</emphasis>, you first have to instantiate a
					<emphasis>JavaTask</emphasis> object and, then, to specify the class you want to be executed by this task (To make your own executable, please refer to the
					proper section <xref linkend="define_executable_java"/>).
					In addition, you can add arguments with which the task will be launched.
					These launching arguments will be given to the Java executable as a Map.
					Take a look at the example hereafter so as to see how to use the Java API to create a Java task
					(also see the Java Documentation of the Scheduler to learn more):
				</para>
				<programlisting language="java">
//create a Java Task with the default constructor
JavaTask aTask = new JavaTask();
//add executable class or instance
aTask.setExecutableClassName("org.ow2.proactive.scheduler.examples.WaitAndPrint");
//then, set the desired options
aTask.setName("task 1");
aTask.setDescription("This task will do something...");
aTask.addGenericInformation("key","value");
aTask.setMxNumberOfExecution(3);
aTask.setRestartTaskOnError(RestartMode.ELSEWHERE);
aTask.setCancelJobOnError(false);
aTask.setResultPreview(UserDefinedResultPreview.class);
//add arguments (optional)
aTask.addArgument("foo",new Boolean(true));
aTask.addArgument("bar",new Integer(12));
aTask.addArgument("test","test1");

//SCRIPTS EXAMPLE		
//If the script to use is in a file or URL
String[] args = new String("foo","bar");
File scriptFile = new File("path/to/script_file");
//URL scriptURL = new URL("url/to/script_file");
Script script = new SimpleScript(scriptFile, args);
// Script script = new SimpleScript(scriptURL, args);
aTask.setPreScript(script);
//If the script to use is in a Java string for example
Script script = new SimpleScript("Script_content", "type_of_language");
//where type_of_language can be any language supported by the underlying JRE
aTask.setPreScript(script);

//same construction for the post script
aTask.setPostScript(script);

//same construction for the cleaning script
aTask.setCleaningScript(script);

//same construction for the  selection script
//the last parameter is still not used in the current implementation
SelectionScript selScript = new SelectionScript(script, true);
aTask.setSelectionScript(selScript);
				</programlisting>
				<para>
					Once this done, you still have to add your task to your job: 
				</para>
				<programlisting language="java">
//add the task to the job
job.addTask(aTask);
				</programlisting>
				<para>
					Here are some other features than can be performed on tasks such as dependencies or wallTime :
				</para>
				<programlisting language="java">
//admitting task 2 and task 3 has been create just before
//we have to create task 5.
//create a new task
JavaTask task5 = new JavaTask();
//... (fill task5 as described above)
//then specify dependencies by using the addDependence(Task) method
task5.addDependence(task2);
task5.addDependence(task3);
//or use the addDependences(list&lt;Task&gt;) method as shown
//task5.addDependences(new ArrayList&lt;Task&gt;(task2,task3));

//set this task as forked
aTask.setFork(true);
//set a walltime
aTask.setWallTime(10000);
//you can also define a fork environment
ForkEnvironment env = new ForkEnvironment();
env.setJavaHome("Your/java/home/path");
env.setJVMParameters("-d12");
aTask.setForkEnvironment(env);
				</programlisting>
				<para>
					To have an exhaustive list of available options and theirs functions, please refer to
					the task explanation section (see <xref linkend="Create_task_explanation"/>).
				</para>
			</section>
		</section>
		
		<section xml:id="Create_native_task"><info><title>Create and add a native task</title></info>
			<para>
				<emphasis>Note</emphasis>: A native task can only be added to a TaskFlow Job.
			</para>
			<para>
				To learn how to create a TaskFlow Job,
				please refer to <xref linkend="Create_TaskFlow_job_xml"/> or <xref linkend="Create_TaskFlow_job_java"/>.
				Once your TaskFlow Job has been created, you can add as many native tasks as needed to perform your application.
				A native task can be any native application such as programs, scripts, processes...
			</para>
			<section xml:id="Create_native_task_xml"><info><title>Create and add a native task using an XML descriptor</title></info>
				<para>
					Take a look at the following example to understand the syntax of a native task:
				</para>
				<programlisting language="xml"><textobject><textdata fileref="scheduler/xml/native_task_simple.xml"/></textobject></programlisting>
				<para>
					The native task is composed of one 'nativeExecutable' tag that specified the executable process to use.
					A set of parameters has also be defined to provide the executable with some arguments. These arguments will be
					appended (according to the Runtime.exec() method) to the command line starting by your native executable.
					This example also shows the definition of two tasks with dependencies. We can easily see that 'task2_native' depends on
					'task1_native'. So 'task2_native' will be executed only once 'task1_native' has finished.
					To put these two tasks inside your TaskFlow job, just put that piece of code into 'taskFlow' tags.
					Here is a complete ready-to-be-scheduled TaskFlow Job:
				</para>
				<programlisting language="xml"><textobject><textdata fileref="scheduler/xml/taskFlow_job_complete_with_native.xml"/></textobject></programlisting>
				<para>
					To have an exhaustive list of available options and theirs functions, please refer to
					the task explanation section (see <xref linkend="Create_task_explanation"/>).
				</para>
				<para>
					As it has been said in <xref linkend="Create_java_task_xml"/>, it is possible to mix Java and Native task inside a taskFlow Job.
					Please refer to this section for more information.
				</para>
			</section>
			<section xml:id="Create_native_task_java"><info><title>Create and add a native task using the Java API</title></info>
				<para>
					To <emphasis>create a native task</emphasis>, you first have to instantiate a
					<emphasis>NativeTask</emphasis> object and, then, to specify the command corresponding to 
					your native task. This command is actually a String array whose first element is the path to the command
					and the following ones represent its arguments.
					Take a look at the following example to see how to create a native task using the Java API
					(see also Java Documentation of the ProActive Scheduler to learn more):
				</para>
				<programlisting language="java">
//create a native task with the default constructor
NativeTask aTask = new NativeTask();
//set the command line with its parameters
aTask.setCommandLine(new String[]{"/path/to/command/cmd","param1","param2");
//then, set the desired options:
aTask.setName("task 1");
aTask.setDescription("This task will do
something...");
aTask.addGenericInformation("key","value");
aTask.setPreciousResult(true);
aTask.setMaxNumberOfExecution(3);
aTask.setRestartTaskOnError(RestartMode.ELSEWHERE);
aTask.setResultPreview(UserDefinedResultPreview.class);

//SCRIPTS EXAMPLE		
//If the script to use is in a file or URL
String[] args = new String("foo","bar");
File scriptFile = new File("path/to/script_file");
//URL scriptURL = new URL("url/to/script_file");
Script script = new SimpleScript(scriptFile, args);
// Script script = new SimpleScript(scriptURL, args);
aTask.setPreScript(script);
//If the script to use is in a Java string for example
Script script = new SimpleScript("Script_content", "type_of_language");
//where type_of_language can be any language supported by the underlying JRE
aTask.setPreScript(script);

//same construction for the post script
aTask.setPostScript(script);

//same construction for the cleaning script
aTask.setCleaningScript(script);

//same construction for the  selection script
//the last parameter is used to specified whether the script is static
//or dynamic
SelectionScript selScript = new SelectionScript(script, true);
aTask.setSelectionScript(selScript);
				</programlisting>
				<para>
					Once this done, you still have to add your task to your job: 
				</para>
				<programlisting language="java">
//add the task to the job
job.addTask(aTask);
				</programlisting>
				<para>
					Here are some other features than can be performed on tasks such as dependencies or wallTime :
				</para>
				<programlisting language="java">
//admitting task 2 and task 3 has been create just before
//we have to create task 5.
//create a new task
NativeTask task5 = new NativeTask();
//... (fill task5 as describe above)
//then specify dependencies by using the addDependence(Task) method
task5.addDependence(task2);
task5.addDependence(task3);
//or use the addDependences(list&lt;Task&gt;) method as shown
//task5.addDependences(new ArrayList&lt;Task&gt;(task2,task3));

//set a walltime to stop the process after the given time even it is not finish
aTask.setWallTime(10000);
				</programlisting>
				<para>
					Here is a last example that describes how to create a native task with a
					<emphasis>dynamic command</emphasis>, that is, a command generated by a script called a
					generation script. The generation script can only be associated to a
					<emphasis>native</emphasis> task: the execution of a generation
					script must set the string variable <literal>command</literal>.
					The value of this variable is the command line that will be executed by
					the ProActive Scheduler as a task execution. The returned string will be parsed
					and transform as a String array according to this example ( '%' is the escape character ):
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para>the string "/path/to/cmd arg1 arg 2 arg% 3 arg%%% 4 5"</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>will generate : [/path/to/cmd,arg1,arg,2,arg 3,arg% 4,5]</para></listitem>
 					</itemizedlist>
					where the first element is the command.
				</para>
				<programlisting language="java">
//create a new native task
NativeTask task2 = new NativeTask();
//create a generation script with a script as shown above
GenerationScript gscript = new GenerationScript(script);
//set the command to execute as a string
task2.setGenerationScript(gscript);
				</programlisting>
				<para>
					To have an exhaustive list of available options and theirs functions, please refer to
					the task explanation section (see <xref linkend="Create_task_explanation"/>).
				</para>
			</section>
		</section>
		
		<section xml:id="Create_ProActive_task"><info><title>Create and add a ProActive task</title></info>
			<para>
				<emphasis>Note</emphasis>: It is only possible to add a ProActive task in a ProActive Job.
			</para>
			<para>
				To learn how to create a ProActive Job,
				please refer to <xref linkend="Create_ProActive_job_xml"/> or <xref linkend="Create_ProActive_job_java"/>.
				Once your ProActive Job created, it is only possible to add <emphasis>ONE</emphasis> ProActive task inside your job.
			</para>
			<section xml:id="define_executable_ProActive"><info><title>Define your own ProActive executable</title></info>
				<para>
					You can create your own ProActive executable by implementing scheduler executable interfaces.
					In this sens, 'executable' means the executed process (that is a Java class in this case).
					Here is an example on how to create your own ProActive executable:
				</para>
				<programlisting language="java">
public class ProActiveExample extends ProActiveExecutable {

	private int numberToFind = 5003;
	
	@Override
	public Serializable execute(ArrayList&lt;Node&gt; nodes) {
		System.out.println("ProActive job started !!");

		// create workers (on local node)
		Vector&lt;Worker&gt; workers = new Vector&lt;Worker&gt;();

		for (Node node : nodes) {
			try {
				Worker w = (Worker)PAActiveObject.newActive(Worker.class.getName(),
						new Object[] { }, node);
				workers.add(w);
			} catch (ActiveObjectCreationException e) {
				e.printStackTrace();
			} catch (NodeException e) {
				e.printStackTrace();
			}
		}

		// create controller Controller controller = new Controller(workers);
		int result = controller.findNthPrimeNumber(numberToFind);

		System.out.println("last prime : " + result);

		return result;
	}
}
				</programlisting>
				<para>
					It is also possible to get a list of arguments that you can give to the executable at its start by
					overriding the init method of the ProActiveExecutable class. How to give arguments to the task will be explain
					later.
					Let's see how you can give a foo, a bar and a test argument to the previous example:
					<programlisting language="java">
private boolean foo;
private int bar;
private String test;

@Override
public void init(Map&lt;String, Object&gt; args) {
	foo = (Boolean)args.get("foo");
	bar = (Integer)args.get("bar");
	test = args.get("test");
}
					</programlisting>
				</para>
				<para>
					This example uses the nodes given in parameters and start 'workers' on them. 
					The <code>execute(nodes)</code> method shows what can be done
					inside this kind of task. For more details about how to use the ProActive API,
					see the appropriate documentation.
					The complete example file can be found under 'samples/jobs_descriptors/Job_ProActive.xml'.
				</para>
				</section>
			</section>
			<section xml:id="Create_ProActive_task_xml"><info><title>Create and add a ProActive task using XML descriptor</title></info>
				<para>
					To understand the syntax of the ProActive task, please take a look at the following example:
				</para>
				<programlisting language="xml"><textobject><textdata fileref="scheduler/xml/ProActive_task_simple.xml"/></textobject></programlisting>
				<para>
					The ProActive Task is composed of one 'proActiveExecutable' tag that specifies the 'ProActiveExecutable' Java class to use.
					A set of parameters has also be defined to provide this executable with some information. These parameters will be
					available into the <code>Map</code> of the <code>init(Map)</code> method into your <code>ProActiveExecutable</code>.
					To put this task inside your ProActive job, just put it between the 'ProActive' tags.
					For this job, it is necessarily to set the number of nodes you want for your ProActiveExecutable.
					Instead of deploying resources as it has to be done in ProActive Suite, the resources are provided by the ProActive Scheduler.
					Here is a complete ready-to-be-scheduled ProActive job:
				</para>
				<programlisting language="xml"><textobject><textdata fileref="scheduler/xml/ProActive_job_complete.xml"/></textobject></programlisting>
				<para>
					Some other options can be set in a ProActive task. Here is a new example of what can be done with
					an XML descriptor:
				</para>
				<programlisting language="xml"><textobject><textdata fileref="scheduler/xml/ProActive_task_script.xml"/></textobject></programlisting>
				<para>
					To have an exhaustive list of available options and their functionalities, please refer to
					the task explanation section at <xref linkend="Create_task_explanation"/>.
				</para>
			</section>
			<section xml:id="Create_ProActive_task_java"><info><title>Create and add a ProActive task using Java API</title></info>
				<para>
					To <emphasis>create a ProActive task</emphasis>, you have first to instantiate a
					<emphasis>ProActiveTask</emphasis> object.
					Then, you have to specify the class you want to start with, by mentioning a
					Class of extending the ProActiveExecutable class (To make your own executable, see the
					proper section <xref linkend="define_executable_ProActive"/>).
					In addition, you can add arguments with which the task will be launched.
					These launching arguments will be given to the ProActive executable as a Map.
					Take a look at the example below to see how to use the task creation Java API
					(see also Java Documentation of the Scheduler to learn more):
				</para>
				<programlisting language="java">
//create a ProActive Task using the default constructor that we'll call 'aTask'
ProActiveTask aTask = new ProActiveTask();
//add executable class or instance
pat.setExecutableClassName("org.ow2.proactive.scheduler.examples.ProActiveExample");
//then, set the desired options : (for example)
aTask.setName("task 1");
aTask.setDescription("This task will do
something...");
aTask.addGenericInformation("key","value");
aTask.setResultPreview(UserDefinedResultPreview.class);
//add arguments (optional)
aTask.addArgument("foo",new Boolean(true));
aTask.addArgument("bar",new Integer(12));
aTask.addArgument("test","test1");
//add number of nodes needed for the application
      pat.setNumberOfNodesNeeded(10);

//SCRIPTS EXAMPLE		
//If the script to use is in a file or URL
String[] args = new String("foo","bar");
File scriptFile = new File("path/to/script_file");
//URL scriptURL = new URL("url/to/script_file");
Script script = new SimpleScript(scriptFile, args);
// Script script = new SimpleScript(scriptURL, args);
aTask.setPreScript(script);
//If the script to use is in a Java string for example
Script script = new SimpleScript("Script_content", "type_of_language");
//where type_of_language can be any language supported by the underlying JRE
aTask.setPreScript(script);

//same construction for the post script
aTask.setPostScript(script);

//same construction for the cleaning script
aTask.setCleaningScript(script);

//same construction for the  selection script
//the last parameter is still not used in the current implementation
SelectionScript selScript = new SelectionScript(script, true);
aTask.setSelectionScript(selScript);
				</programlisting>
				<para>
					To complete your job by adding the task inside the job, add it as followed:
				</para>
				<programlisting language="java">
//add the task to the job
job.setTask(aTask);
				</programlisting>
				<para>
					<emphasis>Note: </emphasis> you can add <emphasis>only one</emphasis> ProActive task in a ProActive job
				</para>
				<para>
					To have an exhaustive list of available options and their functionalities, please refer to
					the task explanation section at <xref linkend="Create_task_explanation"/>.
				</para>
			</section>
			
			<section xml:id="Create_task_explanation"><info><title>Tasks options and explanations</title></info>
				<para>
					As it has been shown in the different examples, it is possible to create 3 types of tasks.
					These 3 types have some common features like name, description, scripts and so on.
					Here are details on each of these common features:
				</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>name</emphasis> -
							name of the task. 
							It can be whatever you want.
							This name must be unique.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>description</emphasis> (optional) - 
							human readable description of the task.
							It is for human use only. This field is optional but it is better to set it.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>genericInformation</emphasis> (optional) - 
							defines some information inside your task.
							This information could be read inside the policy (similar to job's one).
							It can be useful to add new complex scheduling behavior.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>preciousResult</emphasis> (optional - false by default) - 
							defines whether a result of a task is important. 
							For example, in a job result, you could have to retrieve only some task results that are
							important for you. By setting the precious result option to 'true', you will be able
							to retrieve them easily.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>cancelJobOnError</emphasis> (optional - false by default or set to the cancelJobOnError value of its job) - 
							defines whether your job must continue if a user exception or an
							error occurs during this task process. 
							True means that the job
							will immediately stop every remaining running tasks if an error occurs in this task.
							It is useful when there is no need to go further if this task fails.
							If true, the job will be canceled if the maximum number of execution for this task has been reached.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>maxNumberOfExecution</emphasis> (optional - 1 by default or set to the maxNumberOfExecution value of its job) - 
							defines how many times a task will run if it ends with an exception
							or an error code. 
							If the task ends in a normal way, this property has no effect.
							If the task has an exception or an error more than defined in this property, there are 2 possibilities:
							<itemizedlist>
								<listitem>
									<para>
									cancelJobOnError=true: then, the job is canceled.
									</para>
								</listitem>
								<listitem>
									<para>
									cancelJobOnError=false: then, the task ends and the job continues in a normal way.
									</para>
								</listitem>
							</itemizedlist>
							In Both cases, the result is the representation of the error (Exception in Java, error code in native).
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>restartTaskOnError</emphasis> (optional - anywhere by default or set to the restartTaskOnError value of its job) - 
							defines whether this task has to restart on an other resource.
							Possible values are 'anywhere' or 'elsewhere' meaning respectively
							that the concerned task will be restart on any available resources or on a different one.
							A task can be restarted when an exception occurred (Java Task) or when an error code is returned (Native Task) and 
							if the maximum number of execution has not been reached yet. Each time an error occurred, the task is placed in
							a Faulty(n/m) status and the numberOfExecutionLeft count is decreased. 'n' is the current number of executions and
							'm' is the maximum number of executions.
						</para>
						<para>
							Here is a table that sum-up the different possible executions, that can be useful to know the behavior of your job :
						</para>
						<para>
							<figure xml:id="cancel_restart"><info><title>CancelJobOnError and RestartTaskOnError behavior</title></info>
								<mediaobject>
									<imageobject>
										<imagedata scalefit="1" width="70%" contentdepth="70%" align="center" fileref="scheduler/pics/core/cancel-restart.png" format="PNG"/>
									</imageobject>
								</mediaobject>
							</figure>
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>Walltime</emphasis> (optional) - 
							maximum time for the task execution (timeout).
							It can be specified for any task, irrespectively of its type.
							If a task does not finish before its walltime it is terminated by the ProActive Scheduler.
							An example has been given above with the walltime specified. Note that, the walltime
							is defined in a task, thus it can be used for any type of a task.
							The general format of the walltime attribute is [hh:mm:ss], where h is hour, m is minute and s is second.
							The format still allows for more flexibility. We can define the walltime simply as “5”
							which corresponds to 5 seconds, “10” is 10 seconds, “4:10” is 4 minutes and 10 seconds, and so on. 
							
							The walltime mechanism is started just before a task is launched. If a task does finish before its walltime,
							the mechanism is canceled. Otherwise, the task is terminated. Note that the tasks are terminated without
							any prior notice.
							
							If the walltime is specified for a Java task (as in the example), it enforces the creation of
							a forked Java task instead.
							
							When this property is defined and execution exceeds this time, the task ends with an exception.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>fork and forkEnvironment</emphasis> (optional, only for Java Task) - 
							defines respectively whether a task has to be forked and if so, defines the fork environment.
							The purpose of a Forked Java Task is to gain more flexibility with
							respect to the execution environment of a task.
							A new JVM is started with an inherited classpath and (possibly) redefined Java home path and JVM properties.
							It allows to use a JVM from a different provider and specify options to be passed to JVM (like memory usage). 

							A Forked Java Task is defined as a Java Task with a forkEnvironment element.

							A forkEnvironment element aims at providing javaHome and jvmParameters attributes.
							For any undefined attribute a default environment value will be applied. Note that, the javaHome
							attribute points only to the Java installation directory and not the Java application itself.
							
							If the javaHome is not specified then the ProActive Scheduler will execute simply a Java command assuming
							that it is defined in the user path. The 'jvmParameters' attribute is a string composed of a sequence
							of Java options separated by spaces.
							See <xref linkend="Create_java_task"/> for an illustration of their usage. 
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>parameters</emphasis> (optional, only for Java and ProActive Task) - 
							defines some parameters to be transfered to the executable. 
							This is best explained
							in <xref linkend="define_executable_java"/>. Each parameter is define with a name and a value
							and will be passed to the Java Executable as an <code>Map</code>.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>arguments</emphasis> (optional, only for native Task) - 
							defines arguments for your native process. 
							Each argument is define by a value
							that will be appended to the process name to create a String array command line.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>resultPreview</emphasis> (optional) - 
							allows to specify how the result of a task should be displayed in the
							Scheduler graphical client. 
							The user should implement a result preview class
							(extending the
							<literal>
								org.objectweb.proactive.extensions.scheduler.common.task.ResultPreview
							</literal>
							abstract class) which specifies result rendering in two different manners:
						</para>
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									a textual manner, by implementing
									<literal>
										public abstract String getTextualDescription(TaskResult result);
									</literal>.
									This method, similarily to
									<literal>
										String Object.toString()
									</literal>
									should return a <literal>String</literal> object that describes the result.
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									a graphical manner, by implementing
									<literal>
										public abstract JPanel getGraphicalDescription(TaskResult result);
									</literal>.
									This method should return a Swing
									<literal>JPanel</literal>
									object that describes the result.
								</para>
							</listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
						<para>
							Some useful methods to create a specific preview class can be found in
							<literal>
								org.objectweb.proactive.extensions.scheduler.common.task.util.ResultPreviewTool
							</literal>,
							such as automatic display of an image file, or automatic translation between
							windows and unix path.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<!-- TODO gsigety : Add more scripts examples -->
							<emphasis>scripts</emphasis> (optional) -
							The ProActive scheduler supports portable script execution through the
							JSR 223 Java Scripting capabilities. Scripts can be written in any language
							supported by the underlying Java Runtime Environment. They are used in the
							ProActive Scheduler to:
						</para>
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Execute some simple Pre, Post and Cleaning processing: optional pre-script,
									post-script, and cleaning-script
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Select among available resources the node that suits the execution: optional
									selection-script can be associated to a task.
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Dynamic building of a command line for a native task: optional
									generation-script (detailed in next section).
								</para>
							</listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
						<para>
							Here are some details and examples:
						</para>
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									<emphasis>selection script</emphasis> - 
									a selection script is always executed before the task itself
									on any candidate node: the execution of a selection script
									must set the boolean variable <literal>selected</literal>
									, that indicates if the candidate node is suitable for
									the execution of the associated task.
									A java helper (org.ow2.proactive.scripting.helper.selection.SelectionUtils)
									is provided for allowing user to simply make some kind of selections.
									(script samples are available in 'samples/scripts/selection' directory.)
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									<emphasis>pre-script</emphasis> - 
									the pre-script is always executed on the node that has
									been selected by the Resource Manager <emphasis>before</emphasis>
									the execution of the task itself.
									Java helper (org.ow2.proactive.scripting.helper.filetransfer package) is also available
									for file transfer purposes to manage file copies. 
									Some script samples are available in 'samples/scripts/filetransfer' directory.
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									<emphasis>post-script</emphasis>  - the post-script is executed on the same node
									<emphasis>after</emphasis> the task itself and only if this last one has succeed.
									The same helper than for pre-script can be used in the post-script.
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									<emphasis>cleaning-script</emphasis> - the cleaning-script is always
									executed by the Resource Manager <emphasis>after</emphasis> the execution
									of the task itself or after the post-script (if used).
									The same helper than for pre-script can be used in the cleaning-script.
								</para>
							</listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
						<para>
							For pre, post and cleaning script, you can use the file transfer helper classes. It provides easier
							way to copy, paste, transfer files from a host to another. (Examples are available in
							'samples/scripts/filetransfer' directory)
						</para>
						<para>
							To use your favorite script language, you just have to add the two needed jars (engine and implementation)
							in the nodes, Resources Manager and Scheduler classpath.
						</para>
						<para>
							Note: For any script engine or script implementation used in this package or brought by you,
							you have to notice that:
						</para>
						<para>
							THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS "AS IS" AND ANY EXPRESS
							OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY
							AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT OWNER OR
							CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL
							DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE,
							DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER
							IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT
							OF THE USE OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				<para>
					Once your job created, next step is to submit it to the ProActive Scheduler.
				</para>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section xml:id="Submit_a_job"><info><title>Submit a job to the Scheduler</title></info>
			<para>
				The submission will perform some verifications to ensure that a job is correctly formed.
				Then, the job is inserted in the pending queue and waits for executions until free resources
				become available. Once done, the job will be started on the resources deployed by the
				Resource Manager. Finally, once finished, the job goes to the queue of finished jobs and will wait until the user
				retrieves his result.
				Their are three ways to submit a job to the Scheduler described in the following sub-sections.
			</para>
			<section xml:id="Submit_a_job_GUI"><info><title>Submit a job using the Graphical User Interface (Scheduler Eclipse Plugin)</title></info>
				<para>
				To submit a job using the graphical tools, you have first to create a job XML Descriptor.
				Once done, please refer to
				<xref linkend="Scheduler_Eclipse_Plugin"/>.
				</para>
			</section>
			<section xml:id="Submit_a_job_sh"><info><title>Submit a job using the shell command</title></info>
				<para>
					Use the provided shell script <emphasis>userScheduler.[sh|bat]</emphasis> to submit a job using command line.
					This script (bin/[os]/userScheduler.[sh|bat] used to submit a job) has 1 mandatory option and 2 optional :
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								<emphasis>Job to schedule</emphasis> (mandatory) -
								It can be an XML Job descriptor, a simple flat file, or a path to a native command to launch :
								Use -submit followed by the path or the command to give, and :
								<itemizedlist>
									<listitem><para>To schedule an XML job file: use -submit followed by the path of an XML descriptor</para></listitem>
									<listitem><para>To schedule a flat file containing native commands: use -submit followed the by the path of a flat file containing native commands and -cmdf to specify that it is a command file.</para></listitem>
									<listitem><para>To schedule a path to a native command : use -submit followed by the path of the native command to launch, with its launching arguments. Here, it submits a job made of one native task.
									Then, use -cmd to specify that it is a command path.</para></listitem>
								</itemizedlist>
								For -cmd and -cmdf options, you can use aditional parameters. For instance, you can specify a log file that will contain all STDOUT and STDERR of job execution, with -o followed by the path of a file.
								This file is created (emptied if exits) at each beginning of job execution. You can specify a selection script with -s, followed by the path of a selection script file.
								You can specify a job name, with -jn followed by a string specifying a name. These three options (-s, -o and -jn) are not taken into account if -cmd or -cmdf are not specified option, because job name,
								selection scripts and log file are directly specified in the XML job descriptor.
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								<emphasis>The URL of a started scheduler</emphasis> (optional) - 
								To use this option, add a "-u URL" argument. If not mentioned,
								the script will connect to an existing local Scheduler.
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								<emphasis>Your login</emphasis> (optional) - 
								To use this option, add a "-l login" argument
								. If you use this option, only
								your password will be requested.
								Otherwise, both will be.
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</para>
				<para>
					Examples:
				</para>
				<para>
					<emphasis>
						userScheduler.[sh|bat] -submit ../../samples/jobs_descriptors/Job_with_dep.xml -l login -u //localhost:1099/
					</emphasis>
					will submit the <literal>Job_with_dep</literal> job to a local
					ProActive Scheduler on port 1099 with the username 'login', and only your password will be requested.
					Authorized username and password are defined by the administrator.
				</para>
				<para>
					<emphasis>
						userScheduler.[sh|bat] -submit ../../samples/jobs_descriptors/job_native_linux_cmd_file/cmds_file.cmd -cmdf -l demo //localhost/ -jn myJob -o myJob.log
					</emphasis>
					will submit a job defined in a flat file, containing 4 native commands. Job is named "myJob", and a log file named "myJob.log" will be created.
				</para>
				<para>
					<emphasis>
						userScheduler.[sh|bat] -submit ../../samples/jobs_descriptors/job_native_linux_cmd_file/myCmd.sh 4 -cmd -l demo -u //localhost -s ../../samples/scripts/selection/select.rb
					</emphasis>
					will submit the native command "myCmd.sh" with "4" as the only argument. A selection script is associated for this native command: "select.rb".
				</para>
				<para>
					For more information, use -h (or --help) option (i.e. "userScheduler.[sh|bat] -h").
				</para>
			</section>
			<section xml:id="Submit_a_job_java"><info><title>Submit a job using the Java API</title></info>
				<para>
					To connect the ProActive Scheduler and submit a Job using Java API, just proceed as follows:
				</para>
				<programlisting language="java">
//join an existing ProActive Scheduler retrieving an authentication interface.
SchedulerAuthenticationInterface auth = SchedulerConnection.join("//host/");
//connect and log to the Scheduler. Valid username and password are define by the administrator.
UserSchedulerInterface scheduler = auth.logAsUser("username", "password");
// submitting a new job and get the associated id
JobId myJobId = scheduler.submit(job);
				</programlisting>
				<para>
					As you can see, submitting a job will return a Job ID. This is the identification code of
					the submitted Job. It is useful to save it in order to retrieve future information on this job.
				</para>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section xml:id="get_result"><info><title>Get a job result</title></info>
			<para>
				Once a Job is terminated, it is possible to get its result. You can only get the result of the job that you own.
			</para>
			<section xml:id="get_result_GUI"><info><title>Get a job result using the Graphical User Interface (Scheduler Eclipse Plugin)</title></info>
				<para>
				To get a job result using the graphical tools, please refer to
				<xref linkend="Scheduler_Eclipse_Plugin"/>.
				</para>
			</section>
			<section xml:id="get_result_sh"><info><title>Get a job result using the shell command</title></info>
				<para>
					To get the result of you job using a command line, launch the command <emphasis>userScheduler.[sh|bat] -result jobID</emphasis> script in the bin/[os]/ directory.
					This script has 2 optional options:
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								The URL of a started Scheduler ("-u URL" option). If you
								don't use this, it will try to connect to a started scheduler on
								the local host.
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								Your login ("-l login" option). If you use this option,
								only your password will be requested. Otherwise, both will be requested.
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</para>
				<para>
					It will print the result on the screen as the
					toString() Java method could have done it.
				</para>
				<para>
					For more information, use -h (or --help) option (i.e. "userScheduler.[sh|bat] -h").
				</para>
			</section>
			<section xml:id="get_result_java"><info><title>Get a job result using the Java API</title></info>
				<para>
					To do it in Java, use the <emphasis role="bold">getJobResult(JobId)</emphasis> method in the
					<emphasis role="bold"> UserSchedulerInterface </emphasis> interface and the job ID you got when you submitted it.
					A job result is in fact a list of task result ordered in three lists:
				</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							A full list that contains every result
							or exception of every tasks.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							A failed list that contains every result
							or exception returned by a task that
							failed.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							A precious result list that contains
							every result or exception returned by
							the task marked as precious.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				<para>
					This result will be given to you exactly like
					you returned it in your executable. To know
					when a job you have submitted has finished
					its execution, you can subscribe to the
					scheduler to be notified of some events. This
					will be explain in the next section.
				</para>
				<programlisting language="java">
// get the user interface
UserSchedulerInterface scheduler = auth.logAsUser("username", "password");
// get the result of the job
JobResult myResult = scheduler.getJobResult(myJobId);
//look at inside the JobResult to retrieve TaskResult...
				</programlisting>
				<para>
					The above example is useful when you kept a reference of myJobId. If you want to submit a job and disconnect, just keep
					the id as a string (using myJobId.value() ). Then when reconnecting the Scheduler to get the result,
					just use the getJobResult(String jobId) method.
				</para>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section xml:id="Register_events"><info><title>Register to ProActive Scheduler events</title></info>
			<para>
				If you are <emphasis>using the Java API</emphasis>, it is possible to get events from the Scheduler. 
				In order to be notified about the scheduler activities, you can add a Scheduler listener
				that will inform you of some events, like job submitting, job or task finished, scheduling
				state changing... To add a listener, create your listener implementing the
				<emphasis>SchedulerEventListener</emphasis> interface and add it to the scheduler. You will
				then receive the scheduler state containing some information about the current
				scheduling state. See the ProActive Scheduler JAVADOC for more details.
			</para>
			<para>
				It is also possible to specify if you want to receive events concerning your jobs, or any job from any user in the Scheduler.
			</para>
			<programlisting language="java">
//make your listener
SchedulerEventListener mySchedulerEventListener = new SchedulerEventListener () {
	jobStateUpdatedEvent(NotificationData&lt;JobInfo&gt; notification){
		switch(notification.getEventType()){
			case JOB_RUNNING_TO_FINISHED :
				//if my job is finished
				if (notification.getData().getJobId().equals(myJobId)){
					//get its result
					JobResult myResult = scheduler.getJobResult(myJobId);
				}
				break;
		}
	}
	//Implement other methods...
}
//add the listener to the scheduler specified which events you want to receive.
scheduler.addSchedulerEventListener(mySchedulerEventListener, true, SchedulerEvent.JOB_RUNNING_TO_FINISHED);
			</programlisting>
			<para>
				This example shows you how to listen to the scheduler events (only finished job event
				in the previous example). Yet, you can listen for every event you want contained in this interface.
			</para>
			<para>
				For more details and features on the user scheduler interface, please refer to the java Documentation.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section xml:id="scheduler_controller"><info><title>Using the Scheduler controller</title></info>
			<para>
				The Scheduler controller provides a way to interact with the Scheduler. Start it with the <emphasis>bin/[os]/userScheduler.[sh|bat]</emphasis>
				script. You can use it as a command line (as shown
				in some examples above, go to <xref linkend="scheduler_controller_non_interactive"/>) or in interactive mode (go to
				<xref linkend="scheduler_controller_interactive"/>).
			</para>
			<section xml:id="scheduler_controller_non_interactive"><info><title>Command line mode</title></info>
				<para>
					Here is the displayed help when using <emphasis>userScheduler.[sh|bat] -h</emphasis> command:
					<figure xml:id="scheduler_controller_help"><info><title>Scheduler controller help</title></info>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata width="100%" align="center" fileref="scheduler/pics/schedulerControllerHelp.png" format="PNG"/>
							</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>
					</figure>
				</para>
				<para>
				To use the controller as a command line just specify at list one 'ctl' option. Let's illustrate that way with some examples:
				</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>userScheduler.[sh|bat] -l demo -submit path/to/job/xml/descriptor</emphasis>: tries to connect user demo, prompts for
							its password and submits the given XML descriptor file.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>userScheduler.[sh|bat] -l demo -cmd -jn test -submit ls -al</emphasis>: tries to connect user demo, prompts for
							its password and submits the given command line in a job named 'test'. In this case, the <emphasis role="italics">-cmd</emphasis> option forces
							the argument of <emphasis role="italics">-submit</emphasis> option to be a command line.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>userScheduler.[sh|bat] -cmdf -s path/to/a/selection/script -submit path/to/a/text/file</emphasis>: prompts for a username and
							its password and submits the given commands file. It also includes the given selection script file.
							In this case, the <emphasis role="italics">-cmdf</emphasis> option forces
							the argument of <emphasis role="italics">-submit</emphasis> option to be a flat text file that contains
							commands (One command per line, each line will be a task).
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>userScheduler.[sh|bat] -output 12</emphasis>: prompts for a username and
							its password and displays the output written by job 12 if it is finished.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>userScheduler.[sh|bat] -result 34</emphasis>: prompts for a username and
							its password and displays the result of job 34 if it is finished.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>userScheduler.[sh|bat] -priority 56 Lowest</emphasis>: prompts for a username and
							its password and requests the Scheduler to change job 56 priority to 'LOWEST'.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				<para>
					Once the command launched, it will terminate by displaying a successful message or the cause of
					a possible failure as an exception.
				</para>
			</section>
			<section xml:id="scheduler_controller_interactive"><info><title>Interactive mode</title></info>
				<para>
					Another way to interact with the Scheduler is using the interactive mode of the controller. To start it in this mode,
					just execute the bin/[os]/userScheduler.[sh|bat] command without specifying a 'ctl' option:
					<emphasis>userScheduler.[sh|bat] -l demo -u rmi://localhost:1313/</emphasis> is an example which connect the controller
					to a local Scheduler on the port 1313 with 'demo' login.
				</para>
				<para>
					Once connected, type <emphasis role="italics">?</emphasis> or <emphasis role="italics">help</emphasis> to get the list of
					provided functions:
					<figure xml:id="scheduler_controller_i_help"><info><title>Scheduler controller interactive help</title></info>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata width="100%" align="center" fileref="scheduler/pics/schedulerControllerIHelp.png" format="PNG"/>
							</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>
					</figure>
				</para>
				<para>
					The interactive controller is <emphasis role="bold">based on JavaScript language</emphasis> where some methods
					(describe in <xref linkend="scheduler_controller_i_help"/>) have been defined in order to facilitate its usage.
					Here is an example of what can be done with the console:
				</para>
				<programlisting>
  &gt; submit("../../samples/jobs_descriptors/Job_PI.xml");
Job successfully submitted ! (id=1)

  &gt; myId = submit("../../samples/jobs_descriptors/Job_PI.xml");
Job successfully submitted ! (id=2)

  &gt; pausejob(1);
Job 1 paused.

  &gt; resumejob(1);
Job 1 resumed.

  &gt; result(myId);
Job 2 result =&gt;

	 Average1 : 3.1414783733333334
	 Computation3 : 3.1414446
	 Computation4 : 3.14154732
	 Average2 : 3.141520226666667
	 Computation1 : 3.14146984
	 LastAverage : 3.1414993000000004
	 Computation5 : 3.14129996
	 Computation2 : 3.14152068
	 Computation6 : 3.1417134

  &gt; output(myId);
Job 2 output =&gt;

Average1 :
Parameters are :
3.14146984
3.14152068
3.1414446
Average is : 3.1414783733333334

Average2 :
Parameters are :
3.14154732
3.14129996
3.1417134
Average is : 3.141520226666667

LastAverage :
Parameters are :
3.1414783733333334
3.141520226666667
Average is : 3.1414993000000004


  &gt; myResult = result(1)
Job 1 result =&gt;

	 Average1 : 3.14164032
	 Computation4 : 3.14176412
	 Computation3 : 3.14162724
	 Average2 : 3.1416647466666667
	 Computation1 : 3.14182172
	 LastAverage : 3.1416525333333336
	 Computation5 : 3.1416124
	 Computation2 : 3.141472
	 Computation6 : 3.14161772

  &gt; println(myResult.getName());
job_PI
				</programlisting>
				<para>
					As you can see, the provided methods are useful to make basic actions. It is also possible to get
					instances from Scheduler API. As shown, the <emphasis role="italics">myResult = result(1)</emphasis> instruction
					leads to get an instance of JobResult in the 'myResult' variable. As in Java, use the method of the JobResult API
					to get other informations. Here is an example:
				</para>
				<programlisting>
  &gt; prio = myResult.getJobInfo().getPriority();

  &gt; status = myResult.getJobInfo().getStatus();

  &gt; nbfinished =  myResult.getJobInfo().getNumberOfFinishedTasks();

  &gt; duration = myResult.getJobInfo().getFinishedTime()-myResult.getJobInfo().getStartTime();

  &gt; println("priority : "+prio);  println("status : "+status); println("finished tasks : "+nbfinished); println("duration = "+duration+" ms");
priority : Normal
status : Finished
finished tasks : 9
duration = 94386 ms
				</programlisting>
				<para>
					The <emphasis role="italics">exec(...)</emphasis> function provides a way to evaluate a javascript file. For example,
					just insert the code below in a '.js' file with:
				</para>
				<programlisting>
myResult = result(1);
prio = myr.getJobInfo().getPriority();
status = myr.getJobInfo().getStatus();
nbfinished =  myr.getJobInfo().getNumberOfFinishedTasks();
duration = myr.getJobInfo().getFinishedTime()-myr.getJobInfo().getStartTime();
println("priority : "+prio);  println("status : "+status); println("finished tasks : "+nbfinished); println("duration = "+duration+" ms");
				</programlisting>
				<para>
					The result will be exactly the same as the one in the code shown in the previous example.
				</para>
				<para>
					When error occurred in a command, it is possible to show the stack trace on demand. Indeed, the execution stops
					and prompts the user to show the stackTrace or not.
					In order to script this interactive controller, you can disable stack trace on demand. To do so, use the
					<emphasis role="italics">exMode(...)</emphasis> function. The first parameter defines whether the stack trace will be
					displayed while the second one defines if the stack trace has to be displayed every time or on demand.
					Setting the first parameter to 'false' disables the second one.
				</para>
				<para>
					As an example, let's see the following script:
				</para>
				<programlisting>
  &gt; exMode(false);
Exception display mode changed : stack trace not displayed

  &gt; for (i=0;i&lt;5;i++){submit("../../samples/jobs_descriptors/Job_PI.xml")};
Job successfully submitted ! (id=3)
Job successfully submitted ! (id=4)
Job successfully submitted ! (id=5)
Job successfully submitted ! (id=6)
Job successfully submitted ! (id=7)

  &gt; for (i=0;i&lt;5;i++){result(i);}
Error on job 0 : The job represented by this ID is unknow !
Error on job 1 : The job represented by this ID is unknow !
Error on job 2 : The job represented by this ID is unknow !
Job 3 result =&gt;

	 Average1 : 3.1416381333333336
	 Computation4 : 3.14196316
	 Computation3 : 3.14175216
	 Average2 : 3.141720133333333
	 Computation1 : 3.14169736
	 LastAverage : 3.1416791333333336
	 Computation5 : 3.14180604
	 Computation2 : 3.14146488
	 Computation6 : 3.1413912
Job 4 is not finished or unknown !
				</programlisting>
				<para>
					In this case, we get some error messages but no exception and the script can terminate without prompting to view stack trace.
				</para>
			</section>
		</section>
</chapter>
