<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="index"><title>ProActive guided tour</title>
<!--  File: /home/irosenbe/PA_new_doc/docbook-tuto/doc-files/guided_tour/index.html  -->
  
    <para> This tour is a practical introduction to ProActive, giving an illustrated introduction to some
 of the functionnalities and facilities offered by the library.</para>
    <para>First off, we give an explaination on how to install and configure ProActive. Next are
 introduced the different functionalities of the library through some runnning examples. Then are
 given om details on how this is put down in code, and you will be challenged to write your bits
 of code. This should give you practical experience on how to program using ProActive. A section
 on OO-SPMD (Object-Oriented Single Program Multiple Data) will show how to use this programming
 paradigm.</para>
    <para>The guided tour is finished off by the complete N-Body example. This application is first
 written trivially, then some speed-ups are plugged in, to show how ProActive can help you. We
 hope this will help your understanding of the library, and of the concepts driving it.</para>
    <para>If you need further details on how the examples work, check the ProActive <ulink url="http://www-sop.inria.fr/oasis/ProActive/apps/index.xml">applications</ulink>
 page.</para>
    <para>&#160;</para>
    <sect1 remap="h2">
      <title>Installation and setup</title>
      <para>Follow the <ulink url="http://www-sop.inria.fr/oasis/proactive/doc/api/org/objectweb/proactive/doc-files/Installation.xml">instructions</ulink> for downloading and installing ProActive.</para>
      <para>&#160;</para>
      <para>The programming exercises in the first part imply that you :</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para> Don&#39;t forget to add the required libraries to your classpath (i.e. the libraries
 contained in the ProActive/lib directory, as well as either the proactive.jar archive, or the
 compiled classes of proactive (better if you modify the source code)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para> use a policy file, such as ProActive/scripts/proactive.security.policy, with the JVM option
 -Djava.security.policy=/filelocation/proactive.java.policy</para>
        </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
      <para>Set the CLASSPATH as follow :</para>
      <para>Under linux :</para>
      <para>export
 CLASSPATH=.:./ProActive_examples.jar:./ProActive.jar:./lib/bcel.jar:./lib/asm.jar:./lib/log4j.jar:./lib/xercesImpl.jar:./lib/components/fractal.jar:./lib/bouncycastle.jar</para>
      <para>Under windows :</para>
      <para>set
 CLASSPATH=.;.\ProActive_examples.jar;.\ProActive.jar;.\lib\bcel.jar;.\lib\asm.jar;.\lib\log4j.jar;.\lib\xercesImpl.jar;.\lib\components\fractal.jar;.\lib\bouncycastle.jar</para>
      <para>&#160;</para>
      <para>Concerning <emphasis role="underline">the second part</emphasis> of the tutorial (examples of some functionalities):</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para> Note that the compilation is managed by <ulink url="http://jakarta.apache.org/ant">Ant</ulink> ;
 we suggest you use this tool to make modifications to the source code, while doing this
 tutorial. Nevertheless, you can just change the code and compile using compile.sh &lt;the example application&gt; (or compile.bat under windows)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para> The examples used in the second part of this tutorial are provided in the /scripts
 directory of the distribution.</para>
          <para>
 The scripts are platform dependant : .sh files on linux are equivalent to the .bat files on
 windows</para>
        </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="doc-files/guided_tour/pics/screenshots/proactive_directories.jpg" format="JPG"/>            </imageobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="doc-files/guided_tour/pics/screenshots/proactive_directories.svg" format="SVG"/>            </imageobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="doc-files/guided_tour/pics/screenshots/proactive_directories.png" format="PNG"/>            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>
</para>
    </sect1>
  
</chapter>
