<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="ProActive_Scheduler_Matlab">
    <info>
        <title>ProActive Scheduler's Matlab Extension</title>
    </info>

    <section xml:id="Scheduler_Matlab_Overwiew">
        <info>
            <title>Presentation</title>
        </info>
        <section xml:id="Scheduler_Matlab_Motivations">
            <info>
                <title>Motivations</title>
            </info>
            <para>
                <emphasis>Matlab</emphasis>
                is a numerical computing environment and programming
                language. Created by The MathWorks, Matlab allows easy
                matrix manipulation, plotting of functions and data,
                implementation of algorithms, creation of user interfaces,
                and interfacing with programs in other languages.

                As of 2004, MATLAB was used by more than one million people
                in industry and academia.
            </para>
            <para>
                The goal of this extension is to equip Matlab
                with a generic interface to Grid computing. This
                extension allows the deployment of Matlab instances
                on several nodes of the grid (and to use these instances
                like computing engines) and submitting of Matlab
                tasks over the grid. These engines are monitored by a
                central ProActive API. A natural condition is to deploy an
                application (based on this interface) strictly on hosts
                where the Matlab software is installed.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="Scheduler_Matlab_Features">
            <info>
                <title>Features</title>
            </info>
            <para>
                The interface with Matlab inside ProActive comes as a Matlab Toolbox that can be directly accessed from the Matlab environment (ProActive Scheduler Toolbox). The objectives of <emphasis>ProActive Scheduler Toolbox</emphasis> are to provide you with tools that:
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Allow you to run Matlab functions on remote computers.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Do not block the local Matlab session while remote results are being produced.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Allow you to seamlessly retrieve results when you need them, just as if the functions were run locally.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Provide you detailed remote log/output information, altogether with errors if any occurred.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Allow a disconnected mode, jobs can be submitted and the matlab session doesn't need to remain active while the job is processing.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Allow automatic source transfer, data file transfer, transfer of local matlab workspace and other configurable options.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="SciMat_Matlab_Installation">
        <info>
            <title>Installation for Matlab</title>
        </info>

        <para>
            The toolbox can be found at <emphasis>SCHEDULING/extensions/matlab/toolbox</emphasis>. To install it inside Matlab, simply add the path to the toolbox to matlab search path, via the <emphasis>addpath</emphasis> command at the matlab prompt:
        </para>
        <screen>>> addpath('/home/fviale/eclipse_workspace/Scheduling_Clean/extensions/matlab/toolbox/')</screen>

        <para>
            The full documentation of <emphasis>ProActive Scheduler Toolbox</emphasis> will then be available on the Matlab Help:
        </para>
        <figure xml:id="SciMat_Matlab_Help"><info><title>ProActive Scheduler Toolbox on the Matlab Help</title></info>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata scalefit="1" width="220%" contentdepth="220%" fileref="images/png/matsci/PSTHelp.png" format="PNG"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
        <para>Please refer to the Matlab Help for a detailed explanation of ProActive Scheduler Toolbox usage.</para>
        <para>Alternatively you can download the pdf version of this help : <emphasis xlink:href="http://proactive.inria.fr/release-doc/Matlab/ProActiveSchedulerToolbox.pdf">ProActiveSchedulerToolbox.pdf</emphasis></para>
        <!--<figure xml:id="ProActiveSchedulerToolbox"><info><title>Taskflow job example</title></info>
				<mediaobject>
					<textobject>
						<textdata fileref="files/ProActiveSchedulerToolbox.pdf" />
					</textobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>-->


    </section>


</chapter>
