<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
	xml:id="Accounting">
	<info>
		<title>Accounting</title>
	</info>
	<para>
		The users (clients) of the Resource Manager may request and offer nodes for computation. To keep track on how much node time
		was consumed or contributed by a particular user, the Resource Manager associates a user to an account.	
	</para>
	<para>
		More precisely, the nodes can be manipulated by the following basic operations available to the users:
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					The <emphasis>ADD</emphasis> operation is a registration of a node into the Resource Manager
					initiated by a user considered as a node provider.
				 </para>
				<para>
					A node can be added, through the API, as a result of a deployement process, through an agent or manually from the command line interface.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					The <emphasis>REMOVE</emphasis> operation is the unregistration of a node from the Resource Manager.
				</para>
				<para>
					A node can be removed, through the API, by a user or automatically if it is unreachable by the Resource Manager.					
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					The <emphasis>GET</emphasis> operation is a node reservation, for an unknown amount of time, by a user considered as a node owner.
				</para>
				<para>
					For example, the ProActive Scheduler can be considered as a user that reserves a node for a task computation.
				</para>						
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					The <emphasis>RELEASE</emphasis> operation on a reserved node by any user.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>				
	</para>	
	<para>
		The following accounting data is gathered by the Resource Manager:
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para><emphasis>The used node time</emphasis>: The amount of time other users have spent in using the resources of a particular user.</para>
				<para>
					More precisely, for a specific node owner, it is the sum of all time intervals from <emphasis>GET</emphasis> to <emphasis>RELEASE</emphasis>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><emphasis>The provided node time</emphasis>: The amount of time a user has offered resources to the Resource Manager.</para>
				<para>
					More precisely, for a specific node provider, it is the sum of all time intervals from <emphasis>ADD</emphasis> to <emphasis>REMOVE</emphasis>.
				</para>				
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><emphasis>The provided node count</emphasis>: The number of provided nodes.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</para>

	<para>
		The accounting information can be accessed through a JMX client or through the Resource Manager GUI.
	</para>
</section>
