<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="rm-install">
<info><title>Installation guide</title></info>
	<section xml:id="Requirements"><info><title>Requirements</title></info>
		<para>
			The ProActive Parallel Suite consists of the following products
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis>ProActive Programming</emphasis> enabled the creation of parallel and
					distributed applications. If you decided to implement your parallel
					computations in the application running simultaneously on nodes
					it has all the means to do it. The nodes in this case cannot
					be shared among different users.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis>ProActive Resourcing</emphasis> helped to organize your resources.
					This product includes ProActive Programming and expands its capabilities to
					deploy nodes on different infrastructures and share them among users.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis>ProActive Scheduling</emphasis> allowed to schedule your task flow.
					The scheduler includes the ProActive Resourcing and, as a consequence, ProActive
					Programming and allows to represent your parallel computations in sequence of
					jobs and tasks with dependencies.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>
			Before downloading one of this product, just think of how your computations will
			be represented and where it will be executed.
		</para>
		<para>
			ProActive is written in Java and requires Java 1.6 (or higher). It is
			strongly recommended to use <link xlink:href="http://java.sun.com/javase/downloads/index.jsp">Java from Oracle</link> as all the testing is done with it.
			Once Java intalled on your system, it is required to define <emphasis>JAVA_HOME</emphasis>
			environment variable.
			<warning><para>
			If you need a Java 1.5 version, please contact ActiveEon at contact@activeeon.com.
			</para></warning>
		</para>
		<para>
			Depending on your network topology, firewall configuration and your needs, it may be required
			to open some ports for the resource manager. For instance, when you are deploying nodes
			to the cloud, the resource manager has to be visible from outside.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section xml:id="unpack"><info><title>Downloading and unpacking</title></info>
		<para>
			Actually, ProActive does not require installation. Just <link xlink:href="http://www.activeeon.com/community-downloads">download</link> one of the products
			according to your needs and <emphasis>unzip</emphasis> the archive. That's it. The distribution contains
			sources and binaries with all dependencies. To add your cluster to the resource manager
			just <emphasis>copy</emphasis> this folder to each host. By doing this you will be able to start
			ProActive nodes from the resource manager just pointing to the ProActive home.
		</para>
		<para>
			The resource manager and scheduler graphical user interfaces are written as Eclipse RCP plugins
			and can be embedded into Eclipse or launched as standalone applications. Download appropriate
			version for your platform, unzip and run it. It already has ProActive inside, so nothing has to
			be installed on your system (except Java of course).
		</para>
	</section>
</chapter>
