<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="RM_Virtualization"
		  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <info><title>Virtualized infrastructure</title></info>

  <section xml:id="Virtualization_Overview"><info><title>Hardware Virtualization Overview</title></info>
	<para>
		Virtualized Infrastructure here means a part of an Infrastructure that runs a virtualization
		software. This virtualized infrastructure can then be used as a resource pool for Resource
		Manager execution. A brief introduction about how to install and use the virtualization
		software handled by the Resource Manager is given below. The following section is dedicated
		to explain the use of the Resource Manager for such an infrastructure.
	</para>
	<para>
		Hardware virtualization allows to run several operating systems on a unique machine. This is done thanks
		to a specific software called <quote>Virtual Machine Monitor</quote> ( vmm ). Every virtualization solutions
		need a particular operating system to work ( <quote>Dom0</quote> in case of bare metal, vmm and
		<quote>host OS</quote> in case of hosted virtualization, we will dig deeper in this later ). The vmm can either
		emulates specific hardware devices or grants access to real hardware to the virtual machine ( or guest operating
		system ie. vm ). One thus benefits many features for different purposes. We identify 2 kinds of vmm:
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis>Type 1 hypervisor</emphasis> ( or bare metal ).
				</para>
				<para>
					This type of hypervisor is named "bare metal" because it doesn't need any
				operating system beneath to work. Depending on what kind of product you
				use, you will benefit different drivers for different hardware and,
				maybe, won't be able to get the software functional because of unsupported
				hardware ( see a description at:
				<link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hypervisor">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hypervisor</link> ). The most often,
				you'll need a <quote>DOM 0</quote> virtual machine, which is in fact the operating
				system that stands for your workspace, to manage your virtual infrastructure. The
				virtual machine monitor (VMM) itself is a small footprint software (about 50Mo) which
				will only check and schedule underlying hardware access. To set up your virtual environment
				you need an extra software ( xm for XenOss, xe for XenServer, vmx for ESX ... ) which is useable
				directly from your DOM 0. This type of hypervisor is, in general, more efficient and faster than
				other hypervisors as it implements its own hardware access policy at the lowest possible level and
				because you avoid overhead induced by an underlying operating system.
				Here are some well-known type 1 hypervisors:
				<link xlink:href="http://community.citrix.com/cdn/xs">XenServer</link>,
				<link xlink:href="http://www.microsoft.com/hyper-v-server/en/us/default.aspx">Hyper-V</link>,
				<link xlink:href="http://www.sun.com/software/products/xvmserver/index.xml">xVM Server</link>,
				<link xlink:href="http://www.vmware.com/products/vi/esx/">VMware ESX/ESXi</link>,
				<link xlink:href="http://www.xen.org/">Xen OSS</link>
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis>Type 2 hypervisor</emphasis> ( or hosted ).
				</para>
				<para>
				This type of hypervisor is running on top of an operating system and is seen as a common process
				like every virtual machine containers. We can thus measure the host operating system overhead that treat
				the guest operating system as a child process whereas it was more a "brother" in the case of type one
				hypervisor. Furthermore, every kind of virtualization process cannot be used in hosted virtualization
				for some reasons ( browse
				<link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Platform_virtualization">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Platform_virtualization</link>
				for more details). Here are the main type two hypervisors:
				<link xlink:href="http://www.virtualbox.org/">Virtualbox</link>,
				<link xlink:href="http://www.vmware.com/products/server/">VMware Server</link>,
				<link xlink:href="http://www.qumranet.com/">KVM</link>
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</para>
	<para>
		The most important point a user has to be informed of is the network part. We can essentially distinguish three sorts of
		network provisions:
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis>Bridge Networking.</emphasis> Here, the network routing is made at the 3rd level of the OSI/ISO stack. Your computer's NIC binded to your
					company/internet network is setup in <quote>PROMISCUOUS MODE</quote> to intercept not only packet intended for the host/dom0 IP but also
					for newly created Virtual interfaces designed to provide network to virtual machines. Depending on what kind of virtualization product you use, you
					may have to create the virtual interfaces by yourself ( brctl/openvpn on linux systems &amp; Network Manager on Windows ). With this solution, your
					guest operating systems are part of the company network like your host computer. That means a fully point-to-point connectivity between both
					hardware/virtual machine on your network.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis>Nat/Route.</emphasis> The network routing is also made at the 3rd level of the OSI/ISO stack. This time, a newly created virtual interface will
					ensure POST/PRE-ROUTING &amp; MASQUERADE for your virtual machine to have network access. It is really easy to find such configuration example on the internet
					( <link xlink:href="http://www.revsys.com/writings/quicktips/nat.html">Here for linux for instance</link> ).
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis>NAT user.</emphasis> This time network routing is made at the virtualization software layer. For the outer world ( the host machine comprised )
					the virtual machines are unreachable. The most often, the associated subnet has the netmask 10.0.0.1/24, 10.0.0.1 &amp; 10.0.0.2 are the IPs for the host
					machine ( only seen by the virtual machines ) and every virtual machines belongs to its own subnet ( virtual machines can't speak to each other ).
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="Virtualization_InfrastructureManager"><info><title>Virtualized Infrastructure Management</title></info>
  <para>
	The way RM Nodes belonging to a virtualized infrastructure are acquired is divided in three steps:
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis>Contact the virtual machine manager</emphasis> and ask it to clone and power on the virtual
					machines that will be used to run RM Nodes. To get that done, you must provide the pieces of information
					required: the virtual machine monitor's url ( this one depends on the underlying virtual infrastructure,
					we will dig deeper into this subject later ), a virtual machine monitor's user and his password, the
					template virtual machine you want to use ( the most often, the name of the virtual machine as it appears
					in your virtual infrastructure management tool ), the maximum number of this instance the virtual machine
					monitor can handle. Some other information are needed but are related to the virtual infrastructure such
					as the host capacity ( the number of RM Node that will be launched per virtual machine ), the Resource
					Manager's url and credentials to be able to register the created RM Nodes.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis>Start the RM Nodes</emphasis> once the virtual machine starts. This step requires the retrieval
					of the information provided in the previous step from the inside of the virtual machine. To get that done
					we provide template daemon files located in scripts/virtualization ( rm-node-starter.bat &amp;
					rm-node-starter.sh ). These scripts needs additional tools to work. To get more information about
					how does it work, refer to the section of the corresponding virtualization tool
					<link linkend="virtualization-vmware">VMware</link>, <link linkend="virtualization-xenserver">XenServer</link>, <link linkend="virtualization-virtualbox">Virtualbox</link>
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis>Register RM Node</emphasis> in the Resource Manager. This step can be done either by
					remote node registration or by local node registration. In the first case, the newly started
					nodes remotely connect to the Resource Manager and register themselves as available ( this
					method is applied if you provide the Resource Manager's url ). The latter ensures a local node registration,
					this means that once the RM Nodes are started, they communicate their url to the virtual machine
					monitor. The Resource Manager on its side "poll" the virtual machine monitor to know when the
					newly created RM Nodes are available and register them. This second method is more attractive
					if you want to use Scheduler aware policies for example because the Resource Manager will
					cache available nodes for futur reuse. In case of remote registration, you must ensure that
					the Resource Manager is able to contact RM Nodes ( that means that the communication protocol
					used for communication is well suited for the kind of network connection used. For example, in case
					of NAT User, you'll have to use ProActive Message Routing Protocol i.e PAMR ).
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <para>
	Here is a snapshot of the panel for the information keyboarding:
	<figure>
	<info><title>Virtual Infrastructure NodeSource creation dialog</title></info>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata scalefit="1" width="55%" contentdepth="55%" fileref="images/png/vi-nodesource.png" format="PNG"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
	</figure>
	or
	<programlisting>
$RM_HOME>./bin/unix/rm-client -uc --createns virtual -infrastructure org.ow2.proactive.resourcemanager.nodesource.infrastructure.VirtualInfrastructure Virtualbox VMMUrl VMMUser VMMPwd VMTemplate VMMax hostCapacity PAConfig RMUrl RMCredentials
	</programlisting>
  </para>
  <para>
	The <emphasis>Infrastructure</emphasis> field inform the Resource Manager about what kind of virtualized infrastructre
	to manager. At this time, only <link linkend="virtualization-vmware">vmware</link>,
	<link linkend="virtualization-xenserver">xenserver</link> and <link linkend="virtualization-virtualbox">virtualbox</link>
	are supported.
	The <emphasis>PA Config</emphasis> field points to a file describing ProActive properties used to update
	RM Nodes environment. You can thus dinamically precise the node's environment for example a precise network communication
	protocol.
	The <emphasis>RM Url</emphasis> field holds the Resource Manager's url that will be used to connect remotely, from the virtual
	machine, by the RM Nodes to register themself as available. If you don't fill this field, local node registration will
	be used. The "Load from file" button alows you to fill field providing a file of "key = value" entries. The key
	must be the field's name without whitespaces ( case sensitive, an example can be found in config/rm/deployment/vmm.properties ).
  </para>
	  <section xml:id="virtualization-vmware">
		<info><title>VMware Products</title></info>
		<para>
			This section deals with VMware products <link xlink:href="http://www.vmware.com/products/vi/">Virtual Infrastructure compliant</link>.
			To use this kind of products for Resource Manager Node acquisition, you must first create your virtual machine, then,
			copy your Resource Manager release inside the virtual machine. Next, use one of the scripts that we provide
			( scripts/virtualization/rm-node-starter.[sh|bat] ) to register a new service on your virtual machine.
			Note that for both case, you have to get python installed and available in the PATH variable, and especially for
			windows, you must use the <link xlink:href="http://www.microsoft.com/Downloads/details.aspx?FamilyID=9d467a69-57ff-4ae7-96ee-b18c4790cffd&amp;displaylang=en">AutoEXnt software</link>.
			You also need to install VMware Guest Tools ( from vi web management interface, right panel, install guest tools ), and
			have them available in the PATH variable.
			You must modify the rm-node-starter scripts in the virtual machine to match your current Resource Manager setup.
		</para>
		<para>
			Once you have your virtual machine template correctly installed, you can use it from the Resource Manager as
			a RM Node pool. The <emphasis>Infrastructure</emphasis> field appearing on the snapshot above must contain the value "vmware".
			The <emphasis>VMM Url</emphasis> field holds the address of your VMware virtual machine monitor. For VMware
			Virtual Infrastructure compliant products, the most often, it is either http://yourAddress:8222/sdk
			or https://youAddress:8333/sdk by default. If you decide to provide a <emphasis>VM Max</emphasis> number
			greater than 1, the Resource Manager is allowed to clone the template virtual machine for provisionning.
			The clone feature for VMware product is provided by the product itself. The clone virtual machine shares
			the entire set of device of the cloned virtual machine. The templates virtual disk(s) is(are) attached
			to the clone in independent-nonpersistent mode, that means that every power off on the clone will
			erase every data modification made since last startup. Note that during the clone up time, the template
			virtual machine cannot be used anymore as the virtual disk(s) is(are) locked by the clone.
			When the clone virtual machines aren't used anymore, they are destroyed. If a problem occurs during destruction
			time, the best way to come back to a clean environment state is to detach every virtual disk from the clone virtual
			machines ( not from the template ) and to remove every clone ( check the "Delete this virtual machine's files
			from the disk" when confirmation is asked. This way, all disks but the template one will be removed ).
		</para>
	  </section>
	  <section xml:id="virtualization-xenserver">
		<info><title>XenServer</title></info>
		<para>
			This section deals with Citrix's XenServer product.
			To use this kind of products for Resource Manager Node acquisition, you must first create your virtual machine, then,
			copy your Resource Manager release inside the virtual machine. Next, use one of the scripts that we provide
			( scripts/virtualization/rm-node-starter.[sh|bat] ) to register a new service on your virtual machine.
			Note that for both case, you have to get python installed and available in the PATH variable, and especially for
			windows, you must use the <link xlink:href="http://www.microsoft.com/Downloads/details.aspx?FamilyID=9d467a69-57ff-4ae7-96ee-b18c4790cffd&amp;displaylang=en">AutoEXnt software</link>.
			You must modify the rm-node-starter scripts in the virtual machine to match your current Resource Manager setup.
		</para>
		<para>
			Because Citrix doesn't provide any equivalent of VMware guest tools, we use the embeded mysql server to
			hold deployment information. To be able to access these data from the inside of the virtual machine, we
			use the python XenAPI.py lib to connect to the running XenServer and get the pieces of information.
			They are stored in the XenServer DataStore at the VirtualMachine object level as a Hashtable. Every
			data holded by this table are retrieved thanks to one of the virtual machine MAC address ( XenServer
			ensures that every MAC address allocated are different ). Thus, to be sure that the Node acquisition will
			be effective, you must ensure the uniqueness of MAC address for your entire virtual infrastructure.
			<emphasis>You also need to fill</emphasis> the associated server information located in the file
			scripts/virtualization/xenserver/xenserver.py in the virtual machine, <emphasis>xenServerAddress</emphasis> : the url of the
			XenServer running your virtual machine, <emphasis>xenServerUserID</emphasis> : the username you use to
			connect to your XenServer and his password: <emphasis>xenServerUserPWD</emphasis>.
		</para>
		<para>
			Once you have your virtual machine template correctly installed, you can use it from the Resource Manager as
			a RM Node pool. The <emphasis>Infrastructure</emphasis> field appearing on the snapshot above must contain the value "xenserver".
			The <emphasis>VMM Url</emphasis> field holds the address of your XenServer.
			By default this is the http url of the server. If you decide to provide a <emphasis>VM Max</emphasis> number
			greater than 1, the Resource Manager is allowed to clone the template virtual machine for provisionning.
			The clone feature is provided by the virtual machine monitor. The way XenServer clone a virtual machine rely
			on the underlying disk store file system type. If you want to enable efficient clone feature ( using
			differential disks ) you must ensure that the virtual disks used by your template virtual machine are stored
			on a EXT3 base store ( the default store is LVM base ). To change this characteristic refer to this
			<link xlink:href="http://www.tokeshi.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=5025">good tutorial</link>.
		</para>
	  </section>
	  <section xml:id="virtualization-virtualbox">
		<info><title>xVM Virtualbox</title></info>
		<para>
			This section deals with Sun's xVM Virtualbox product.
			To use this kind of products for Resource Manager Node acquisition, you must first create your virtual machine, then,
			copy your Resource Manager release inside the virtual machine. Next, use one of the scripts that we provide
			( scripts/virtualization/rm-node-starter.[sh|bat] ) to register a new service on your virtual machine.
			Note that for both case, you have to get python installed and available in the PATH variable, and especially for
			windows, you must use the <link xlink:href="http://www.microsoft.com/Downloads/details.aspx?FamilyID=9d467a69-57ff-4ae7-96ee-b18c4790cffd&amp;displaylang=en">AutoEXnt software</link>.
			You also need to install Virtualbox Guest Tools ( from Virtual Machine window, devices, install guest additions ), and
			have them available in the PATH variable.
			You also must modify the rm-node-starter scripts in the virtual machine to match your current Resource Manager setup.
		</para>
		<para>
			Once you have your virtual machine template correctly installed, you can use it from the Resource Manager as
			a RM Node pool. The <emphasis>Infrastructure</emphasis> field appearing on the snapshot above must contain the value "virtualbox".
			The <emphasis>VMM Url</emphasis> field holds the address of the vboxwebsrv program shiped with xVM Virtualbox.
			We recommend to run it with a -t parameter set to 20. Note that the default value for the -p parameter is
			18083, that means that the default VMM Url would http://vboxwebsrvAddress:18083.We also notices that some vboxwebsrv releases
			had some troubles with authentication. If it is your case, just submit the following command:
			<programlisting>
						VBoxManage setproperty websrvauthlibrary null
			</programlisting>
			and restart vboxwebsrv.
			If you decide to provide a <emphasis>VM Max</emphasis> number
			greater than 1, the Resource Manager is allowed to clone the template virtual machine for provisionning.
			The clone feature is not provided by xVM Virtualbox itself. To emulate it, you must snapshot the template
			virtual machine. The snapshot for Virtualbox is in fact the creation of a new differential disk hierarchy.
			That means that every newly created virtual machine attached to this snapshot will create a new differential
			disk. When the clone virtual machines aren't used anymore, they are destroyed. If a problem occurs during destruction
			time, the best way to come back to a clean environment state is to remove every clone virtual machine and from the
			virtual disk management window, remove every virtual disk belonging to the snapshot hierarchy of the template virtual
			machine that are not attached to a virtual machine.
		</para>
	  </section>
  </section>
</section>
