<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="Scheduler_Eclipse_Plugin"><info><title>ProActive Scheduler Eclipse Plugin</title></info>

	<para>
		<emphasis role="bold">
			Scheduler Eclipse Plugin
		</emphasis>
		is a
		<emphasis role="bold">graphical client</emphasis>
		for remote monitoring and control of ProActive Scheduler
		(see
		<xref linkend="user_manual"/>
		), including remote submission of XML-defined jobs (see
		<xref linkend="Create_job_xml"/>
		).
	</para>
	<para>
		The Scheduler Eclipse Plugin is available in two forms:
	</para>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				A
				<emphasis role="bold">
					Java stand alone application
				</emphasis>
				based on
				<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://wiki.eclipse.org/index.php/Rich_Client_Platform">
					Eclipse Rich Client Platform (RCP)
				</link>
				, available for any platform (Windows, Linux, Mac
				OSX, Solaris...).
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				A set of
				<emphasis role="bold">
					<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.eclipse.org">
						Eclipse
					</link>
					plugins
				</emphasis>: 
				with all functionalities within the stand
				alone application, enhanced with a tool that makes
				easier the scheduling and monitoring of jobs and
				applications.
			</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<section xml:id="Starting_GUI"><info><title>Starting  Scheduler Graphical User Interface</title></info>
		<para>
			Depending on the way you get the Scheduler plugin, just follow one of this step:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>
					<emphasis role="bold">If you are using the stand alone application</emphasis>, just start it using
					provided executable ("Scheduler" on unix, "Scheduler.exe" on Windows).</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem><para>
					<emphasis role="bold">If you are using the Eclipse plugins set</emphasis>, install it as an eclipse plugin
					and restart Eclipse. Then select the Scheduler Perspective.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			Then, go to <emphasis role="bold">Window-&gt;Open Perspective-&gt;Other...-&gt;Scheduler</emphasis>
			(it could be already opened as it is the default perspective).
		</para>
		<para>
			Once started, the first screen displayed is the following one:
			<figure xml:id="Scheduler_Welcome_screen"><info><title>Scheduler welcome screen</title></info>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata scalefit="1" width="220%" contentdepth="220%" fileref="scheduler_plugin/pics/Screen1.jpg" format="JPG"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
		</para>
	</section>
	
	<section xml:id="Connect_GUI"><info><title>Connect to an existing Scheduler</title></info>
		<para>
			A Scheduler has to be already started before connecting the Scheduler GUI. If no scheduler has been started, please refer
			to <xref linkend="scheduler_installation"/>.
		</para>
		<para>
			To connect to an existing Scheduler, just right click on the empty area in the middle of the windows and click on
			"Connect the ProActive Scheduler" in the context menu as shown below:
			<figure xml:id="RC_screen"><info><title>Scheduler connection (1)</title></info>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata scalefit="1" width="220%" contentdepth="220%" fileref="scheduler_plugin/pics/RC_screen.jpg" format="JPG"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
		</para>
		<para>
			Some information are now requested in order to establish the connection:
			<figure xml:id="connectToSchedulerDialog"><info><title>Connection dialog</title></info>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata scalefit="1" width="70%" contentdepth="70%" fileref="scheduler_plugin/pics/connectToSchedulerDialog.png" format="PNG"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
		</para>
		<para>
			<emphasis role="bold">Enter required information</emphasis> about the remote scheduler
			and click on <emphasis role="bold">OK</emphasis>.
			Url is made of the protocol, the host name on which the Scheduler is started and the port on
			which it is listening.
			Then, enter your user/admin name and password.
		</para>
		<para>
			<emphasis>Note</emphasis>: If you check "log as admin" and your login is an admin one,
			you'll be able to do more actions than an "simple" user (see <xref linkend="Scheduler_composing_controlPanel_admin"/>).
			Connection right is performed by Scheduler itself, you won't be able to connect as admin with a 'user' name.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="Scheduler_perspective"><info><title>Scheduler perspective</title></info>
		<para>
			Scheduler plugin provides the
			<emphasis role="bold">
				Scheduler
				<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://help.eclipse.org/help31/index.jsp?topic=/org.eclipse.platform.doc.user/gettingStarted/qs-43.htm">
					perspective
				</link>
			</emphasis>
			displayed in the <xref linkend="schedulerPerspective"/>.
		</para>
		
		<figure xml:id="schedulerPerspective"><info><title>Scheduler Perspective</title></info>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata scalefit="1" width="220%" contentdepth="220%" fileref="scheduler_plugin/pics/GUI_perspective.jpg" format="JPG"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>

		<para>
			This perspective defines the following set of
			<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://wiki.eclipse.org/index.php/FAQ_What_is_a_view%3F">
				views
			</link>:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="bold">Jobs</emphasis> view - shows pending, running and finished jobs in the scheduler.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="bold">Console</emphasis> view - shows jobs standard and error output (on demand).
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="bold">Tasks</emphasis> view - displays detailed informations on tasks contained
					in the selected job.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="bold">Users</emphasis> view - displays information about connected user.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="bold">Jobs Info</emphasis> view - displays all information of the selected job.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					 <emphasis role="bold">Result Preview</emphasis> view - displays a textual or graphical preview on
					the selected task result. A simple click will show the internal view while the double click start
					an external result preview (as a pictures editor or viewer) if provided.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					A <emphasis role="bold">Control panel</emphasis> is provided at the top right of the windows in order
					to manage jobs and the Scheduler itself.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>


	<section xml:id="Scheduler_composing"><info><title>Views composing the perspective</title></info>
		<section xml:id="Scheduler_composing_jobs"><info><title>Jobs view</title></info>
			<para>
				The main view is obviously the jobs one:
			</para>
			<figure xml:id="jobsView"><info><title>Jobs view</title></info>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%" fileref="scheduler_plugin/pics/jobsView.png" format="PNG"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>
				The control panel (on upper right) is described in the <xref linkend="Scheduler_composing_controlPanel"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				This view is composed of 3 panels that represent respectively pending, running and finished jobs. In each panel you
				can watch many different information about jobs, like their states, names, IDs, progress...
				It is also possible to switch between vertical panel presentation and horizontal panel presentation as it will be described later.
			</para>
			<para>
				In each panel, the list of jobs can be ordered by column. 
			</para>
			<note><para>
			 You can connect the same existing Scheduler with
		  		more than one interface on more than one host if you want to monitor it from different hosts.</para>
			</note>
			
		</section>
		
		<section xml:id="Scheduler_composing_console"><info><title>Console view</title></info>
			<figure xml:id="consoleView"><info><title>Console view</title></info>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata scalefit="1" width="55%" contentdepth="55%" fileref="scheduler_plugin/pics/consoleView.png" format="PNG"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>
				This view displays selected job standard and error output (only on demand).
			</para>
		</section>
		
		<section xml:id="Scheduler_composing_tasks"><info><title>Tasks view</title></info>
			<figure xml:id="tasksView"><info><title>Tasks view</title></info>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%" fileref="scheduler_plugin/pics/tasksView.png" format="PNG"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>
				This view provides a lot of information on every tasks composing a job like:
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para><emphasis>Id</emphasis> - task id generated by the Scheduler</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para><emphasis>State</emphasis> - task status to know if it is finished, running, etc...</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para><emphasis>Name</emphasis> - task name given by the user</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para><emphasis>Host name</emphasis> - host name on which the task is executed</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para><emphasis>Start time</emphasis> - task start time</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para><emphasis>Finished time</emphasis> - task finished time</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para><emphasis>Re-run</emphasis> - 
							In the column "Re-run", the first number represents how many times the task
							<emphasis>has already been</emphasis> re-executed, and the second number represents how many times the task <emphasis>can be</emphasis> re-executed
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para><emphasis>Description</emphasis> - The user description of the task</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				</para>
				<para>
					In this view, the list of tasks can be ordered by column. 
				</para>
		</section>
		
		<section xml:id="Scheduler_composing_info"><info><title>Job Info view</title></info>
			<figure xml:id="jobInfoView"><info><title>Job Info view</title></info>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata scalefit="1" width="55%" contentdepth="55%" fileref="scheduler_plugin/pics/jobInfoView.png" format="PNG"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>
				This view provides many informations on the selected job like:
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para><emphasis>Id</emphasis> - job id generated by the Scheduler, can be useful to get the result of your job outside of the GUI.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para><emphasis>State</emphasis> - job status to know if it is pending, running, paused...</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para><emphasis>Name</emphasis> - job name given by the user that has submitted this job</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para><emphasis>Priority</emphasis> - current job priority (this can be changed to accelerate its execution)</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para><emphasis>Pending tasks number</emphasis> - number of pending tasks</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para><emphasis>Running tasks number</emphasis> - number of running tasks</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para><emphasis>Finished tasks number</emphasis> - number of finished tasks</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para><emphasis>Total tasks number</emphasis> - total number of tasks composing the job</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para><emphasis>Submitted time</emphasis> - job submitted time</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para><emphasis>Started time</emphasis> - job start time</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para><emphasis>Finished time</emphasis> - job finished time</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para><emphasis>Description</emphasis> - user description of the job</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
		</section>
		
		<section xml:id="Scheduler_composing_result"><info><title>Result Preview</title></info>
			<figure xml:id="resultPreviewView"><info><title>Result Preview</title></info>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata scalefit="1" width="60%" contentdepth="60%" fileref="scheduler_plugin/pics/resultPreviewView.png" format="PNG"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>
				This view displays result of the selected task (selected in task view), according to the ResultPreview field.
				This preview is powerful because of the generic way that will be used to perform the display.
				It is possible to redefine the displaying behavior by implementing the <emphasis>ResultPreview</emphasis> abstract class.
				Using this mechanism, it is possible to use an external tool or soft to display the result like an image viewer for picture
				(see <xref linkend="Create_task_explanation"/> for details). Here is an example of what can be done:
			</para>
			<figure xml:id="resultPreviewView"><info><title>Result Preview</title></info>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata scalefit="1" width="60%" contentdepth="60%" fileref="scheduler_plugin/pics/resultPreviewView2.png" format="PNG"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
		</section>
		
		<section xml:id="Scheduler_composing_controlPanel"><info><title>Scheduler control panel</title></info>
			<para>
				This part explains how to use the control panel available at the top right of the Scheduler.
				The control panel goal is to manage the different jobs and the Scheduler itself.
				Let's start with the possibilities offered to a user:
			</para>
			<para>
				<figure xml:id="control_panel"><info><title>Control Panel</title></info>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata scalefit="1" width="150%" contentdepth="150%" fileref="scheduler_plugin/pics/control_panel.jpg" format="JPG"/>
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
			</para>
			<section xml:id="Scheduler_composing_controlPanel_user"><info><title>User controls</title></info>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para>
						<emphasis>[1] Connect/Disconnect the Scheduler</emphasis> - use this button to
						display the "Connect to scheduler" dialog in order to establish a connection to a remote ProActive Scheduler.
						Once connected this button disconnects the user from the current connected Scheduler.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem><para>
						<emphasis>[2] Switch between vertical and horizontal jobs view</emphasis> - use this button to
						switch between the view that displays the three list of jobs vertically and the one that
						displays them horizontally. Horizontal view can be used to see more informations about the listed jobs but
						less jobs can be seen.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem><para>
						<emphasis>[3] Enlarge the job queue of your choice</emphasis> - use this button to
						enlarge the queue (pending/running/finished) of your choice. This will display the selected view in
						the whole space.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem><para>
						<emphasis>[4] Submit a Job from an XML file</emphasis> - use this button to
						submit a new job to the Scheduler. This action will request you for an XML job descriptor.
						If you don't know how to create such a descriptor, please refer to <xref linkend="Create_job_xml"/>.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem><para>
						<emphasis>[5] Submit a file containing native commands</emphasis> - use this button to submit a job defined in flat file.
						If you don't know how to create such a job descriptor, please refer to <xref linkend="flat_file_job"/>.
						This button opens a wizard for submitting this kind of job (see section  <xref linkend="flat_file_wizard"/>).</para>
					</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>					
					<para>
						For the next actions, note that you can also interact with the jobs that <emphasis>you</emphasis> have submitted (that you own).
						To use these actions, just select a job and click on the desired button. Multiple selection is allowed.
					</para>
					<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para>
						<emphasis>[6] Pause/Resume a Job</emphasis> - use this button to
						pause a pending or running job, and to resume a paused job. Note that it is not possible to pause a running task.
						So once a job paused, each running task will be finished. If a task has to restart for any reasons,
						it will be paused instead of restarted.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem><para>
						<emphasis>[7] Select Job priority</emphasis> - use this button to
						change the priority of your job. Allowed priorities for a user are:</para>
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem><para>
								Normal</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem><para>
								Low</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem><para>
								Lowest</para>
							</listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
					</listitem>
					<listitem><para>
						<emphasis>[8] View selected job output</emphasis> - use this button to
						view the selected job output. Job output is in fact the output that comes from the different
						tasks from both standard output and standard error stream.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem><para>
						<emphasis>[9] Kill the selected job</emphasis> - use this button to
						kill a job. The job will be terminated immediately, removed from the queue where it was, and its 
						results will be lost.</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				<para>
					All these actions that can be performed in the control panel can be also executed from the right click context menu.
					To view the result of your task, select one in the tasks view and the result preview will be displayed automatically.
				</para>
			</section>
			<section xml:id="Scheduler_composing_controlPanel_admin"><info><title>Administrator controls</title></info>
				<para>
					All actions allowed in user mode are also allowed in Administrator mode.
					Moreover, you can execute any action on any job even you are not the owner of this job.
					It is also possible for an administrator to do the following operations:
				</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para>
						<emphasis>[6] Select Job priority</emphasis> - use this button to
						change the priority of a job. Allowed priorities for an Administrator are the same
						as the user plus the following one:</para>
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem><para>
								Idle: Priority lower than the 3 User priorities.</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem><para>
								High: Priority higher than the 3 User priorities.</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem><para>
								Highest: Highest priority that can be affected.</para>
							</listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
					</listitem>
					<listitem><para>
						<emphasis>[A] Stop the Scheduler</emphasis> - This action places the Scheduler in a mode
						where no job can be submitted anymore until a restart.
						Nevertheless, all running tasks will be terminated.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem><para>
						<emphasis>[B] Freeze the Scheduler</emphasis> - The behavior is the same as those of the stop
						button except that job can still be submitted.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem><para>
						<emphasis>[C] Pause the Scheduler</emphasis> - This action put the Scheduler in a Pause status.
						Job can be submitted again but no job will go to the running queue. Every running job will terminate.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem><para>
						<emphasis>[D] Resume the Scheduler</emphasis> - Put the Scheduler to the normal scheduling mode, that is, to the Started mode.
						This action can be performed when the scheduler is Frozen or Paused.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem><para>
						<emphasis>[E] Shutdown the Scheduler</emphasis> - Put the Scheduler in its shutdown sequence.
						Submitting job is no longer available. It will wait for every pending and running job to be terminated.
						Once done, the Scheduler will shutdown and disconnect.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem><para>
						<emphasis>[F] Kill the Scheduler</emphasis> - Force the Scheduler to terminate immediately.
						This action kills every task and job, get the resources back to the Resource Manager and kill the Scheduler.</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section xml:id="flat_file_wizard"><info><title>Command file job submission</title></info>
			<para>Once you have defined a file containing the path to native commands to submit (see <xref linkend="flat_file_job"/>), this wizard allows you to submit it.
			Main page provides you with a way to specify additional parameters for your job:
			</para>
			<para>
				<figure xml:id="flat_wizard1"><info><title>Control Panel</title></info>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata scalefit="1" width="150%" contentdepth="150%" fileref="scheduler_plugin/pics/flat_wizard1.jpg" format="JPG"/>
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
			</para>
			<para>
			<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para>
						<emphasis>job name</emphasis> - enter a name for your job.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem><para>
						<emphasis>command file</emphasis> - click on browse button for choosing your file containing native commands using a file chooser dialog.
						This file chooser dialog shows only files suffixed by ".cmd".
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem><para>
						<emphasis>selection script</emphasis> - click on browse button and choose a selection script to associate to each native task of your job.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem><para>
						<emphasis>path for log file</emphasis> - enter a path to a log file that will contain all STDOUT and STDERR of job execution.
								This file is created (emptied if exits) at each beginning of job execution.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem><para>
						<emphasis>Cancel whole job if one of the commands fails</emphasis> - if you check that, the Scheduler will stop all executions of your commands if one fails.
						Scheduler assumes that a failed native command is a command that has a return code different from 0.
						</para>
					</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			</para>
			<para>
			Clicking on  the Next button, you will see a brief summary of your job:
			</para>
			<para>
				<figure xml:id="flat_wizard2"><info><title>Control Panel</title></info>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata scalefit="1" width="150%" contentdepth="150%" fileref="scheduler_plugin/pics/flat_wizard2.jpg" format="JPG"/>
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
			</para>
			<para>
			Click on Finish to launch submission. Native commands are scheduled in parallel.
			If there are enough free resources (nodes) for every command, all commands will be launched simultaneously.
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>
</chapter>
