<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="viewDocbook.css"?>
<chapter id="TroubleShooting">
  <title>ProActive Troubleshooting</title>

  <para>In this section we present common problems encountered while trying to
  use ProActive. For further assistance, or if you cannot solve a problem, feel free to post your question on the
  ProActive mailing list <ulink
  url="http://forge.objectweb.org/mail/?group_id=7">proactive@objectweb.org
  </ulink>. Make sure that you include a
    precise description of your problem along with a full copy of the error
    message.</para><sect1>
    <title>Common problems</title>

    <para>If you encounter any problem with installing ProActive and running
    the examples, please make sure you correctly followed all the steps
    described in the previous chapter. If it doesn't help, here is a list of the most common
    mistakes:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Permission denied when trying to launch
        scripts under Linux</emphasis> Files have the wrong permissions set. 
        You will have to change the permissions by executing <literal>chmod
        755 *.sh</literal></para> in the <literal>ProActive/scripts/unix directory</literal>. The command will 
        set the files to executable and readable for all users and also writeable for the current user.
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Java complains about not being able to
        find the ProActive classes.</emphasis> Your <literal>CLASSPATH</literal>
        environment variable does not contain the entry for classes belonging to ProActive,
        ASM, Log4, Xerces, Fractal, or BouncyCastle.
        <literal>ProActive.jar,asmXX.jar, log4j.jar,
        xercesImpl.jar, fractal.jar, bouncycastle.jar</literal> must be in
        your <literal>CLASSPATH</literal>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Java complains about denial of
        access.</emphasis> If you get the following exceptions, you probably
        didn't change the file java.policy as described in <xref lang=""
        linkend="Create_Java_Policy" />.</para>
       
      <programlisting lang="java"><textobject><textdata fileref="code_snippets/java_policy_error.txt"/></textobject></programlisting>
      
      
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Java complains on log4j
        initialization</emphasis> If you get the following message, you
        probably made a mistake when giving the
        <literal>-Dlog4j.configuration</literal> property to the java command.
        Be sure that the given path is right, try also to add <literal>file:</literal> before the
        path.</para>
<programlisting lang="java"><textobject><textdata fileref="code_snippets/log4j_notfound_error.txt"/></textobject></programlisting>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Examples and compilation do not work at
        all under Windows system:</emphasis> Check if your java installation
        is not in a path containing spaces like <literal>C:\Program Files\java or
        C:\Documents and Settings\java</literal>. Batch scripts do not run
        properly when JAVA_HOME is set to such a directory. The solution is to install the JDK under a
        space-free path (e.g. <literal>C:\java\j2sdk....</literal> or <literal>
        D:\java\j2sdk... </literal> ) and then set the <literal>JAVA_HOME </literal> environment variable
        accordingly.</para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
      	<para>
      		<emphasis role="bold">Java complains about unsupported classes:</emphasis> Check
      		that you are using a JRE that is at least version 1.5. since ProActive needs 
      		certain features that are only available starting from Java 1.5.
      		<programlisting lang="java"><textobject><textdata fileref="code_snippets/jdk_version_error.txt"/></textobject></programlisting>
      		
      		
      	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="TroubleShooting_html_loggers">
    <title>Enabling the loggers</title>

    <para>To enable the debugging logger the following log file can be
    used:</para>

	<programlisting lang="java"><textobject><textdata fileref="code_snippets/enable_debugging_loggers.txt"/></textobject></programlisting>

    <para>In this file, the relevant loggers can be uncommented (by removing
    the leading #). For example, the deployment loggers
    are activated with the following lines:</para>

	<programlisting lang="java"><textobject><textdata fileref="code_snippets/enable_deployment_loggers.txt"/></textobject></programlisting>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="dbdoclet.id.TroubleShooting_hostname_ip">
    <title>Hostname And IP Address</title>

    <para>To function properly, ProActive requires machines to have a
    correctly configured hostname and domain name. If the name of a machines
    is not properly configured, then remote nodes will be unable to locate the
    machine.</para>

    <para>To test if the involved machines are properly configured, in Linux/Unix
    you can run the following commands:</para>

	<programlisting lang="java"><textobject><textdata fileref="code_snippets/hostname_errors.txt"/></textobject></programlisting>

    <para><literal>hostname</literal> should print the hostname
    of the machine as known by the other hosts, and <literal
    role="bold">hostname -i</literal> should return the network interface (IP number)
    accessible by other machines.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="dbdoclet.id.TroubleShooting_dns">
    <title>Domaine name resolution problems</title>

    <para>To work around misconfigured domain names ProActive can be activated
    to use IP adresses through the following java property:</para>

	<programlisting lang="java"><textobject><textdata fileref="code_snippets/misconfigured_domains.txt"/></textobject></programlisting>

    <para>This property should be given as parameter to Java virtual machines
    deployed on computers that have names that do not resolve properly.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="dbdoclet.id.TroubleShooting_rmi_tunneling">
    <title>RMI Tunneling</title>

    <para>ProActive provides RMI tunneling through ssh for crossing firewalls
    that only allow ssh connections. Things to verify when using rmissh
    tunneling:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>ProActlive/lib/ganymed-ssh2-build210.jar must be included in the <literal>CLASSPATH</literal> of the
        concerned machines.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The JVM that is only accesible with ssh must be started using:
        <literal>-Dproactive.communication.protocol=rmissh</literal></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A key without a passhprase must be installed on the machine
        accepting connections with ssh. It should be possible to log into the
        site without using an ssh-agent and without providing a
        password.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="dbdoclet.id.TroubleShooting_public_remote_method_calls">
    <title>Public remote method calls</title>

    <para>Methods that will be called remotely on an Active Object must be
    public. While Java will impose this restriction between classes of
    different types, this problem usually takes place when invoking a remote
    method on an object of the same type.</para>

	<programlisting lang="java"><textobject><textdata fileref="code_snippets/public_method_requirement.txt"/></textobject></programlisting>

  </sect1>
</chapter>