<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<refentry version="5.0-subset Scilab" xml:id="Introduction" xml:lang="en"
          xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
          xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
          xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
          xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
          xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <info>
        <pubdate>$LastChangedDate: 2011-07-20 18:41:39 +0100 (mer., 20 july 2011)$</pubdate>
    </info>
    <refnamediv>
        <refname>Introduction</refname>

        <refpurpose>Introduction to the ProActive Toolbox</refpurpose>

    </refnamediv>

    <refsection>
    <title>Introduction</title>


    <para><emphasis>ProActive Scheduler Toolbox</emphasis> is a Scilab toolbox designed to provide interaction with the <emphasis>ProActive Scheduler</emphasis>, part of ProActive Parallel Suite.

<emphasis>ProActive Parallel Suite</emphasis> is an innovative Open Source solution (OW2) for parallel, distributed, multi-core computing.

ProActive features Java Parallel Programming seamlessly integrated with Scheduling and Resource Management. ProActive simplifies the programming and execution of parallel applications on Linux, Windows and Mac, together with the management of resources such as Desktop, Servers, Clusters, Enterprise GRIDs and Clouds.

        The objectives of ProActive Scheduler Toolbox are to provide you with tools that:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Allow you to run Scilab functions on remote computers.
                 </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Do not block the local Scilab session while remote results are being produced.
                 </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Allow you to seamlessly retrieve results when you need them, just as if the functions were run locally.
                 </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Provide you detailed remote log/output information, altogether with errors if any occurred.
                 </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Allow automatic source transfer, data file transfer, and other configurable options.
                 </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
  </refsection>
    <refsection>
        <title>See Also</title>
        <simplelist type="inline">
            <member>
                <link linkend="Installation">Installation</link>
            </member>
            <member>
                <link linkend="PAsolve">PAsolve</link>
            </member>
             <member>
                <link linkend="PAconnect">PAconnect</link>
            </member>
        </simplelist>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
        <title>Authors</title>

        <simplelist type="vert">
            <member>The ProActive Team, Fabien Viale</member>
        </simplelist>
    </refsection>
</refentry>