<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="Overview"><info><title>Overview</title></info>
<!-- <!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V5.0//EN" "docbook.dtd">  -->
	<section xml:id="overview"><info><title>Overview</title></info>
		<para>
			Executions of parallel tasks on distributed
			resources (what we call 'nodes'), such as networks of desktops or clusters, require
			a main system for managing resources and handling task
			executions: <emphasis role="bold">a batch scheduler</emphasis>.
			 A batch scheduler provides an abstraction of resources for
			users. The scheduler enables users to submit jobs, containing one or  several tasks, and
			then to execute these tasks on available
			resources. It allows several users to share a same pool of resources and
			also to manage issues related to distributed
			environment, such as failing resources.
			The ProActive Scheduler is connected to a Resource Manager providing therefore the resource
			abstraction.
		</para>

		<para>
			The Scheduler is accessible either from
			a Java programming API  or
			a command-line based job submitter.
			In the following chapters, we will also present how the
			scheduler works, what policies govern the job management,
			how to create a job and how to get the jobs and the nodes
			state using either the administration shell or the GUI.
			The graphical user and administration interface
			which can be plugged in the scheduler core application
			is presented in <xref linkend="Scheduler_Eclipse_Plugin"/>).
			The graphical interface has been developed as an Eclipse RCP Plugin.


		</para>
	</section>
	<section xml:id="scheduler_installation"><info><title>Scheduler Installation</title></info>
		<para>
			The Scheduler archive contains a sources folder, a distribution folder that contains every library used
			by the ProActive Scheduler, a bin folder that contains every starting script, and a sample directory including
			lots of job XML descriptors and scripts examples (see <xref linkend="user_manual"/> to know what a job descriptor is).
			More folders are available but these are the ones which are needed to start.
		</para>
		<para>
			ProActive is written in Java and requires Java 1.6 (or higher). It is
			strongly recommended to use <link xlink:href="http://java.sun.com/javase/downloads/index.jsp">Java from Oracle</link> as all the testing is done with it.
			Once Java is installed on your system, it is required to define <emphasis>JAVA_HOME</emphasis>
			environment variable.
			<warning><para>
			If you need a Java 1.5 version, please contact ActiveEon at contact@activeeon.com.
			</para></warning>
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>
				First of all, start a command shell and go into the <emphasis>bin/[os]</emphasis> directory
				 into your installed scheduler home path.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem><para>
				Then launch the <emphasis>scheduler-start-clean[.bat]</emphasis> script to create the database
				and launch the Scheduler.
				This database is used to store ProActive Scheduler activities and to offer fault tolerance.
				The scheduler will start and connect to the Resources Manager that either you have already launched
				or that the scheduler has created if no Resources Manager has been found. Scheduler starting sequence is finished when
				<code>Scheduler successfully created on rmi://hostname:port/</code> is displayed.</para>
				<para>
					At this point the ProActive Scheduler is started with 4 available nodes.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					What you can do now is submitting a job. To do so, just start the <emphasis>scheduler-client[.bat]</emphasis> script with
					proper parameters (in the same directory). Using
					<emphasis>scheduler-client[.bat] -submit ../../samples/jobs_descriptors/Job_8_tasks.xml</emphasis>,
					this will request for login and password and then, submit this job to the scheduler. The default login and password,
					is <emphasis>user pwd</emphasis>.
				</para>
				<para>
					Once executed, you can see that the scheduler is now scheduling this job. You can also see the Scheduler activity
					by starting the Scheduler Eclipse Plugin : the Graphical User Interface for the Scheduler.
					To do so, just uncompress the Scheduler_Plugin archive and start the <emphasis>Scheduler[.exe]</emphasis> launcher.
					The first screen presents a non-connected Scheduler interface. Just right click, then connect.
					You will be requested for a started Scheduler URL, user name and password. If you followed this quick start step by step,
					just fill URL field with <emphasis>rmi//localhost:1099/</emphasis> where 1099 is the default ProActive port for RMIRegistry.
					Finally, enter <emphasis>user</emphasis> for the user name and <emphasis>pwd</emphasis> in the password field.
					For further information on the GUI, please refer to the Scheduler Eclipse plugin documentation.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
<!--	<warning><para> Some features of ProActive Scheduling rely on Java Scripting API (JSR 223), which is bugged under MacOSX/Java 1.5.0_16:-->
<!--	some JSR 223 specific classes contained in the AppleScriptEngine.jar (loaded from the boot classpath) are compiled under Java 1.6. As a consequence, using-->
<!--	default Java 1.5.0_16 for starting any part of ProActive Scheduling (including graphical clients and worker nodes) can lead to the following exception (if-->
<!--	scripts capabilities are used):</para>-->
<!--	<para>-->
<!--	<code>-->
<!--	java.lang.UnsupportedClassVersionError: Bad version number in .class file-->
<!--	</code>-->
<!--	</para>-->
<!--	<para>-->
<!--	To fix this issue, you must remove or rename the AppleScriptEngine.jar from /System/Library/Java/Extensions directory.-->
<!--	</para></warning>-->
	</section>
	<section xml:id="scheduler_concept"><info><title>Scheduler Basics</title></info>

		<section xml:id="what_is_job"><info><title>What is a Job ?</title></info>
			<para>
				A <emphasis role="bold">Job</emphasis> is the entity to be submitted to the scheduler. It is
				composed of one or more <emphasis role="bold">tasks</emphasis>.</para>
				<para>There is one type of job, described hereafter:
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis role="bold">TASKSFLOW</emphasis> - represents a job containing a bag of
							tasks, which can be executed either in parallel or
							according to a dependency tree. Tasks
							inside this job can be either Java (A task written in Java extending
							a given interface) or Native (Any native process).
							Each task can be a single process or an MPI application (Execution starts with a given
							predefined number of resources on which the user can start the application).
						</para>
					</listitem>

					<!--  <listitem>
						<para><emphasis role="bold">PARAMETER SWEEPING (not yet implemented)</emphasis>, is a
						job that represents multiple executions of one type of task with
						different given parameters. It is typically executed in parallel.
						The tasks inside this job can also be Java or Native. </para>
						</listitem>-->
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>

			<para>
				A finished job contains all task results provided by the whole process.
				However, if you want to highlight a result which is more important,
				you can mark its corresponding task as
				<emphasis role="bold">precious</emphasis>
				in order to retrieve their result easily in the job
				result. If the job termination has been caused by a failure, then the finished job
				contains the causes of the exception. Further details on how to
				create a job and the different options can be found in
				<xref linkend="Create_job"/>
				.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section xml:id="what_is_task"><info><title>What is a Task ?</title></info>

			<para>
				The
				<emphasis role="bold">Task</emphasis>
				is the smallest schedulable entity. It is included in a
				<emphasis role="bold">Job</emphasis>
				(see
				<xref linkend="what_is_job"/>
				) and will be executed in accordance with the scheduling
				policy (see
				<xref linkend="scheduling_policy"/>
				) on the available resources.
			</para>

			<para>
				There are 3 types of tasks:
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis role="bold">JAVA</emphasis> - its execution is defined by a Java class
							extending the
							<code>
								org.ow2.proactive.scheduler.common.task.executable.JavaExecutable
							</code>
							class.
						</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis role="bold">NATIVE</emphasis> - its execution can be any user program, a compiled C/C++ application, a shell
							or batch script. A native task can be specified by a simple command line,
							 or by a 'generation script' that can dynamically
							generate the command line to be executed (for instance, according to the computing node's operating system
							wherein the task is executed).
						</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis role="bold">SCRIPT</emphasis> - its execution is defined by code written in a scripting language supported by
							<link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scripting_for_the_Java_Platform">JSR 223</link>. By default Java
							supports Javascript.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>

			<para>
				During its execution, a task can crash due to the host (computing node) or
				code failure. The Scheduler solves this potential problem
				by offering  parameterizable tasks
				which can be restarted a set number of times (see maxNumberOfExecution in section <xref linkend="Create_add_task"/>).
			</para>

			<para>
				A task may optionally be defined with 4 kinds of
				scripts (selection-script, pre-script, post-script and cleaning-script)
				which allow selection and configuration of suitable resource for a given
				task  before and after task
				execution (see	<xref linkend="Create_add_task"/>).
			</para>

			<para>
				Dependencies between tasks can also be defined. This
				aspect is detailed in the next section.
			</para>
		</section>


		<section xml:id="how_dependences"><info><title>Dependencies between tasks</title></info>

			<para>
				Dependencies can be set between tasks in a TaskFlow job.
				It provides a way to execute your tasks in a specified
				order, but also to forward result of an ancestor
				task to its children as parameter. Dependency between
				tasks is then both a temporal dependency and a data
				dependency.
			</para>

			<figure xml:id="scheduler_job_img"><info><title>Taskflow job example</title></info>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata scalefit="1" width="70%" contentdepth="70%" align="center" fileref="images/png/schedulerJob.png" format="PNG"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>

			<para>
				In this example, an 8 task job is defined (where job's
				type is TaskFlow). As you can see, task 4 depends on
				task 1, task 5 depends on tasks 2 and 3, and so on... In other
				words, task 4 will wait for the end of task 1 before
				starting and task 5 will wait for the end of task 2
				<emphasis>AND</emphasis>
				3... In addition, the order in which you specify
				that task 5 depends on task 2 and 3 is very important.
				Indeed, if you set the list of dependencies for task 5
				as "2 then 3", the result of these two tasks will therefore be
				given to task 5 (as parameter) in this order.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section xml:id="scheduling_policy"><info><title>Scheduling Policy</title></info>

			<para>
				By default, the Scheduler will schedule tasks
				according to the default <emphasis role="bold">
				FIFO </emphasis> (First In First Out) priority
				policy. If a job needs to be scheduled quickly, increase its priority,
				or ask your administrator for another policy.
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>
</chapter>
