<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 id="Customization">
  <title>Stylesheet Customization</title>

  <para>Ok, now you're nearly a docbook guru? You want to get right down to
  the entrails of the machinery? OK, hop on and enjoy the ride! Here are a few
  notes on how you should go about customizing the output. That means,
  changing how the pdf and html are written.</para>

  <sect2 id="directory">
    <title>File hierarchy</title>

    <para>The files for configuration are the following:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem><para>
        <emphasis role="bold">html.xsl</emphasis> This is where all the
        html specific customizations are made</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>
        <emphasis role="bold">pdf.xsl</emphasis> This is where all the
        pdf specific customizations are made</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>
        <emphasis role="bold">common.xsl</emphasis> This is where all
        the common specifications are made, ie those that go and in pdf and in
        html.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>
        <emphasis role="bold">html.titlepage.templates.xml</emphasis>
        This is the template which modifies the html titlepage layout</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>
        <emphasis role="bold">pdf.titlepage.templates.xml</emphasis>
        This is the template which modifies the pdf titlepage layout</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Please mind:</emphasis> The last two files are
    used to generate one more layer, files called html.titlepage.xsl and
    pdf.titlepage.xsl. The latter should not be edited, as they reflect the
    changes made in the former.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>What you can change</title>

    <para>Basically, in the customization layers, you have full control (just
    do what you want). The only thing is that each block (template,
    variable...) should be described by a comment. That will help later users.
    Long template names are not sufficient. Please take the time to state when
    each is used, and what it does. As customization can get cryptic, make a
    special effort!</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>The Bible</title>

    <para>The book you want to have with you is the following: "DocBook XSL:
    The Complete Guide", Third Edition, by Bob Stayton, online version at
    <ulink
    url="http://www.sagehill.net">http://www.sagehill.net</ulink>.</para>

    <para>Have a look at the index if you just want to change a little
    something in the customization. Parse through it at least once if you
    intend to do some heavy editing. I have found everything I needed in this
    book, but sometimes in unexpected sections.</para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>