<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 id="Customization">
  <title>Stylesheet Customization</title>

  <para>Ok, now you're nearly a docbook guru? You want to get right down to
  the entrails of the machinery? OK, hop on and enjoy the ride! Here are a few
  notes on how you should go about customizing the output. That means,
  changing how the pdf and html are written.</para>

  <sect2 id="directory">
    <title>File hierarchy</title>

    <para>The files for configuration are the following:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem><para>
       <emphasis role="bold">html.xsl</emphasis> This is where all the
       html specific customizations are made</para>
     </listitem>
     
     <listitem><para>
       <emphasis role="bold">pdf.xsl</emphasis> This is where all the
       pdf specific customizations are made</para>
     </listitem>
     
     <listitem><para>
       <emphasis role="bold">common.xsl</emphasis> This is where all
       the common specifications are made, ie those that go and in pdf and in
       html.</para>
     </listitem>
     
     <listitem><para>
       <emphasis role="bold">html.titlepage.templates.xml</emphasis>
       This is the template which modifies the html titlepage layout</para>
     </listitem>
     
     <listitem><para>
       <emphasis role="bold">pdf.titlepage.templates.xml</emphasis>
       This is the template which modifies the pdf titlepage layout</para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Please mind:</emphasis> The last two files are
    used to generate one more layer, files called html.titlepage.xsl and
    pdf.titlepage.xsl. The latter should not be edited, as they reflect the
    changes made in the former.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
   <title>What you can change</title>

    <para>Basically, in the customization layers, you have full control (just
    do what you want). The only thing is that each block (template,
    variable...) should be described by a comment. That will help later users.
    Long template names are not sufficient. Please take the time to state when
    each is used, and what it does. As customization can get cryptic, make a
    special effort!</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>The Bible</title>

    <para>The book you want to have with you is the following: "DocBook XSL:
    The Complete Guide", Third Edition, by Bob Stayton, online version at
    <ulink
    url="http://www.sagehill.net">http://www.sagehill.net</ulink>.</para>

    <para>Have a look at the index if you just want to change a little
    something in the customization. Parse through it at least once if you
    intend to do some heavy editing. I have found everything I needed in this
    book, but sometimes in unexpected sections.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
   <title>Todo list, provided by Denis</title>
   
   <orderedlist>
   
    <listitem>
     <para> Make sure the itemizes are dense (done for html through LI tag in ProActive.css)</para>
    </listitem>
    
    <listitem>
     <para> Color the java key words in program listings. Same for xml files in screens (change these to programlisting lang="XML") </para>
    </listitem>
   
    <listitem>
     <para> In html and pdf the top elements (Part II - Chapter 5) are to be clickeable.</para>
     <para> Part should be on the outside of the page, and chapter on the inside for pdf layout.</para>
    </listitem>
   
    <listitem>
     <para> Ensure no dead links exist (easy with wget --spider OR http://www.dead-links.com/ for html, harder for the pdf).</para>
    </listitem>
    
    <listitem>
     <para> Enable the FAQ.</para>
    </listitem>
    
    <listitem>
     <para> Use this info (google Re: Extending ulink Warren Young) to specialize ulinks in pdf/html [is it needed?].</para>
    </listitem>
    
    <listitem>
     <para> See for direct inclusion of code from the src files (../core/ProActive.java for example) xi:include does not work</para>
     <para> The main files, which are produced in html by javadoc, are to be included in the pdf appendixes</para>
    </listitem>
   
    <listitem>
     <para> Create an index, and put the main words in it</para>
    </listitem>
   
    <listitem>
     <para> Create a reference chapter, with all the ProActive papers, and doucle check citations in manual </para>
    </listitem>
    
    <listitem>
     <para> Add ObjectWeb on the book titlepage</para>
    </listitem>
    
    <listitem>
     <para> Put the Part TOCs on the same page as the PART first page (it's very empty right now) </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <para> In the main TOC, each new part should be highlighted by a page-wide blue line </para>
    </listitem>
    
    <listitem>
     <para> Remove too long captions </para>
    </listitem>
    
    <listitem>
     <para> Check the following schema is always used :</para>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem> <para> Part in White, on blue background </para> </listitem>
       <listitem> <para> Chapter in White, on blue background</para> </listitem>
       <listitem> <para> Sect1 in Blue, on grey background</para> </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
       
    <listitem>
     <para> Decide how much customization should go in the CSS, and how much in the html.xsl  </para>
    </listitem>
    
    <listitem>
     <para> Images should be centered. Code borders should only wrap code, not from left to right margin.   </para>
    </listitem>
    
    <listitem>
     <para> Enable the use of admonitions (see http://sagehill.net/docbookxsl/PrintIcons.html#PrintAdmonGraphics)  </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <para> All important code examples should be wrapped in EXAMPLE tags  </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <para> Have customized titlepage files (including tables?) see http://www.dpawson.co.uk/docbook/styling/titlepage.html</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <para> Have customized titlepage files (including tables?) see http://www.dpawson.co.uk/docbook/styling/titlepage.html</para>
    </listitem>
    
  </orderedlist>
  </sect2>
  
 </sect1>