<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 id="Customization">
  <title>Stylesheet Customization</title>

  <para>Ok, now you're nearly a docbook guru? You want to get right down to
  the entrails of the machinery? OK, hop on and enjoy the ride! Here are a few
  notes on how you should go about customizing the output. That means,
  changing how the pdf and html are written.</para>

  <sect2 id="directory">
    <title>File hierarchy</title>

    <para>The files for configuration are the following:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem><para>
       <emphasis role="bold">common.xsl</emphasis> This is where all
       the common specifications are made, ie those that go and in pdf and in
       html.</para>
     </listitem>
     
     <listitem><para>
       <emphasis role="bold">pdf.xsl</emphasis> This is where all the
       pdf specific customizations are made</para>
     </listitem>
     
    <listitem><para>
       <emphasis role="bold">html.xsl</emphasis> This is where most 
       html specific customizations are made.</para>
     </listitem>
     
     <listitem><para>
       <emphasis role="bold">onehtml.xsl</emphasis> and
       <emphasis role="bold">chunkedhtml.xsl</emphasis>, specifics for html,
       the former on one page, "chunked", one file per chapter, for the 
       latter.</para>
     </listitem>
     
     <listitem><para>
       <emphasis role="bold">ProActive.css</emphasis> Which is yet another
       extra layer on top of the html output.  </para>
     </listitem>
     
    </itemizedlist>

  </sect2>

  <sect2>
   <title>What you can change</title>

    <para>Basically, in the customization layers, you have full control (just
    do what you want). The only thing is that each block (template,
    variable...) should be described by a comment. That will help later users.
    As customization can get cryptic, make a special effort!</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>The Bible</title>

    <para>The book you want to have with you is the following: "DocBook XSL:
    The Complete Guide", Third Edition, by Bob Stayton, online version at
    <ulink url="http://www.sagehill.net">http://www.sagehill.net</ulink>.</para>

    <para>Have a look at the index if you just want to change a little
    something in the customization. Parse through it at least once if you
    intend to do some heavy editing. I have found everything I needed in this
    book, but sometimes in unexpected sections.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
   <title>Todo list, provided by Denis</title>
   
   <orderedlist>
   
    <listitem>
     <para> Ensure no dead links exist (easy with wget --spider OR http://www.dead-links.com/ for html, harder for the pdf).</para>
    </listitem>
    
    <listitem>
     <para> Enable the FAQ.</para>
    </listitem>
    
    <listitem>
     <para> Use this info (google Re: Extending ulink Warren Young) to specialize ulinks in pdf/html [is it needed?].</para>
    </listitem>
    
    <listitem>
     <para> Create an index, and put the main words in it</para>
    </listitem>
   
    <listitem>
     <para> Images should be centered. Code borders should only wrap code, not from left to right margin.   </para>
    </listitem>
    
    <listitem>
     <para> Enable the use of admonitions (see http://sagehill.net/docbookxsl/PrintIcons.html#PrintAdmonGraphics)  </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <para> All important code examples should be wrapped in EXAMPLE tags  </para>
    </listitem>

    
  </orderedlist>
  </sect2>
  
 </sect1>