<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
	xml:id="ProActiveWindowsAgent_89">
	<info>
		<title xml:id="ProActiveWindowsAgent">ProActive Windows Agent</title>
	</info>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>ProActive Windows Agent</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<section xml:id="PWA_Context">
		<info>
			<title>Context</title>
		</info>
		<para>In distributed systems, desktop computers can be an important
			source of computational power. Moreover, one of the definitions of
			grid stands for a type of parallel and distributed system that
			enables the sharing, selection, and aggregation of resources
			distributed across multiple administrative domains based on theirs
			(resources) criteria: availability, capacity and performance. In such
			a context the main purpose of the ProActive Windows Agent is to make
			the configuration of these criteria achievable (schedule working plan
			and limit the shared amount of RAM and CPU).</para>
	</section>
	<section xml:id="PWA_Functionalities">
		<info>
			<title>Functionalities</title>
		</info>
		<para>The ProActive Windows Agent is a Windows Service: a
			long-running executable that performs specific functions and which is
			designed not to require user intervention. The agent is able to
			create a ProActive computational resource on the local machine. This
			resource will be provided to ProActive applications (such as Resource
			Manager) according to a user defined schedule. A tray icon shows the
			state of the agent and allows the user to start/stop it, or modify
			its schedule. The ProActive Windows Agent does not interfere with the
			day-to-day usage of the desktop Windows machine.</para>
		<para>Understanding of ProActive basic concepts is
			required for the comprehension of the following description.</para>
		<para>The core client is a process which:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Loads the user's configuration.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Creates schedules according to the working plan
					specified in the configuration.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Spawns a JVM process that will run a specified java
					class depending on the selected connection type. 3 types of
					connections are available:</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis role="bold">RMI Registration</emphasis>
							- The specified java class will create a ProActive local node as
							a computational resource and register it in a local RMI registry.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis role="bold">Resource Manager Registration
							</emphasis>
							- The specified java class will create a ProActive local node as
							a computational resource and register it in the specified
							Resource Manager, thus being able to execute java or native tasks
							received from the Scheduler.
						</para>
						<para>It's is important to note that a JVM process running tasks
							can potentially spawn child processes.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis role="bold">Custom</emphasis>
							- The user can specify its own java class.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Watches the spawned JVM process in order to comply to
					the following limitations:</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis role="bold">RAM limitation</emphasis>
							- The user can specify a maximum amount of memory allowed for a
							JVM process and its children. If the limit is reached, then all
							processes are automatically killed.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis role="bold">CPU limitation</emphasis>
							- The user can specify a maximum CPU usage allowed for a JVM
							process and its children. If the limit is exceeded by the sum of
							CPU usages of all processes, they are automatically throttled to
							reach the given limit.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Restarts the spawned JVM process in case of failures
					with a timeout policy.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>
	<section xml:id="PWA_Example">
		<info>
			<title>Example</title>
		</info>
		<para>This simple example illustrates how to create an active
			object on a ProActive node created with the ProActive Windows Agent.
			We suppose that the following conditions are verified:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>The agent is installed (see <xref linkend="PWA_Installation"/> for installation) on a
					host with IP address equal to 192.168.1.62</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					It is configured with the
					<emphasis role="bold">RMI registration</emphasis>
					as selected connection type and "toto" as node name.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>Once the agent is started, the following java code gets a
			reference on a remote node and creates an active object on the remote
			node identified by the url "rmi://192.168.1.62:1099/toto"</para>
		<para>
			<programlisting language="java"><textobject><textdata fileref="automatic_snippets/ProActiveWindowsAgent.snip" /></textobject></programlisting>
		</para>

		<para>The output is:</para>
		<screen> --> This ClassFileServer is listening on port 2027
Detected an existing RMI Registry on port 1099
Nb of active objects on the remote node: 0 local runtime hashcode 6588476
Generating class : pa.stub.org.ow2.proactive.resourcemanager.utils._StubTest
Nb of active objects on the remote node: 1 received message: A message from 26670261</screen>
	</section>
	<section xml:id="PWA_Installation">
		<info>
			<title>Installation</title>
		</info>
		<para>The ProActive Windows Agent installation pack is available on
			the official <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://proactive.inria.fr/">ProActive website</uri>. Follow the links and get the latest
			version.</para>
		<note>
			<para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>.Net framework v3.5 or later should be installed on your
						system. If not, the installer will ask you to install it.
						Go to <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.microsoft.com/downloads">http://www.microsoft.com/downloads</uri> and download
						Microsoft .NET Framework Version 3.5 (or later) Redistributable
						Package.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Visual C++ 2008 (or later) Redistributable Package is
						also needed. The installer will install it for you, if not found.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			</para>
		</note>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Run the
					<emphasis role="bold">setup.exe</emphasis>
					file.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Accept the licence agreement.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Select the components you want to install.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Choose the installation folder of the ProActive agent.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Then, the following windows will appear:</para>
				<figure xml:id="PWA_install_config_FIGURE">
					<info>
						<title>Configuration during installation</title>
					</info>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"
								fileref="resourcemanager/pics/install_config.png" format="PNG" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Enter the Java location, usually
							<emphasis role="bold">C:\Program Files\Java\jdk1.6.0_12</emphasis>.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Enter the ProActive location. If you want to use only the "Local Registration" connection (see the "Connection" tab description for more information), the path to a ProActive (programming) directory is sufficient but
							if want to use also the "Resource Manager" connection, you have to specified a path to a
							ProActive Scheduler directory.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Select the service account, if you want to install the
							agent under a specific user account enter the domain ("." or
							hostname is the local domain), user and location.</para>
						<para>Note that you can change these settings at anytime in the
							"services.msc" utility. ("Control Panel->Administrative
							Tools->Services")</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>The installer will check whether the selected user account have the log on service right assignment.</para>
				<para>If not, follow the following steps to add the log on service right assignment:</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para>In the 'Administrative Tools' of the 'Control Panel', open the 'Local Security Policy'.</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>In 'Security Settings', select 'Local Policies' then select 'User Rights Assignments'.</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Finally, in the list of policies, open the properties of 'Log on as a service' policy and add the needed user.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para> At the end of the installation, the user can choose to run the
			ProActive Agent Control utility. This is explained in the next section.
		</para>

		<para>To uninstall the ProActive Windows Agent, simply run
			"Start/Programs/ProActiveAgent/uninstall".</para>
	</section>
	<section xml:id="PWA_Configuration">
		<info>
			<title>Configuration</title>
		</info>
		<para> Launch "Start/Programs/ProActiveAgent/AgentControl" program or
			click on the notify icon if the "Automatic launch" is activated.
			Double click on the tray icon to open the ProActive Agent Control
			window. The dollowing window will appear:</para>
		<para>
			<figure xml:id="PWA_agent_control_FIGURE">
				<info>
					<title>ProActive Agent Control window</title>
				</info>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"
							fileref="resourcemanager/pics/agent_control.png" format="PNG" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
		</para>
		<para> From the ProActive Agent Control window, the user can load a
			configuration file, edit it, start/stop the service and view logs. A
			GUI for editing is provided (explained below). Even if it is not
			recommended, you can edit the configuration file by yourself with
			your favorite text editor.</para>
		<note>
			<para>Configuration files are not compatible from one major release to another.</para>
		</note>
		<para>
			Clicking on "GUI Edit", the following windows appears:
		</para>
		<para>
			<figure xml:id="PWA_config_editor_general_FIGURE">
				<info>
					<title>Configuration Editor window - General Tab
					</title>
				</info>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"
							fileref="resourcemanager/pics/config_editor_general.png" format="PNG" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
		</para>
		<para>In the general tab, the user can specify:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>The ProActive (or Scheduler) location.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>The JVM location (usually something like C:\Program
					Files\Java\jdk1.6.0_12).</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>The number of Runtimes (the number of spawned JVMs).</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>The JVM parameters.</para>
				<para>Note that if the parameter contains <literal>${rank}</literal>, it will be dynamically replaced by the Runtime rank starting from 0.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>The "On Runtime Exit" script. A script executed after a Runtime exits. This can be useful to perform additional cleaning operation.</para>
				<para>Note that the script receives as parameter the pid of the Runtime.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>The user can enable the memory management (disabled by
					default) in order to limit the amount of RAM used by the JVM
					process.</para>
				<para>By default the limit is set to 96 mbytes. Thus, each time the
					JVM process requires more memory, it will be killed as well as its child
					processes.</para>
				<para>The user can extend this limit by giving more memory for
					java tasks (executed by the JVM process) or for native tasks (child
					processes spawned by the JVM process).</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>It is possible to list all available network interfaces by
					clicking on the "Refresh" button and add the selected network
					interface name as a value of the "proactive.net.interface" property
					by clicking on "Use" button. See the ProActive documentation for
					further information.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>
			Clicking on the "Connection" tab, the windows will look like this:
		</para>
		<para>
			<figure xml:id="PWA_config_editor_connection_FIGURE">
				<info>
					<title>Configuration Editor window - Connection Tab
						(Resource Manager Registration)</title>
				</info>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"
							fileref="resourcemanager/pics/config_editor_connection.png" format="PNG" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
		</para>
		<para>In the "Connection" tab, the user can select between three types
			of connections:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="bold">Local Registration</emphasis>
					- creates a local ProActive node and registers (advertises) it in a
					local RMI registry. The node name is optional.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="bold">Resource Manager Registration
					</emphasis>
					- creates a local ProActive node and registers it in the specified
					Resource Manager. The mandatory Resource Manager's url must be like 'protocol://host:port/'. The
					node name and the node source name are optional. Since the Resource Manager requires an
					authentication the user specify the file that contains the credential or use the default one
					usually located in "%USERPROFILE%\.proactive\security" folder.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="bold">Custom</emphasis>
					- the user specifies its own java starter class and the arguments
					to be given to the main method. The java starter class must be in
					the classpath when the JVM process is started.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>
		The user can specify the protocol (rmi or http) to be used by the Runtime for incoming communications.
		</para>
		<para>
		To ensure that a unique port is used by a Runtime, the initial port value will be incremented
		for each Runtime and given as value of the "-Dproactive.SELECTED_PROTOCOL.port" JVM property.
		If the port chosen for a runtime is already used, it is incremented until
		an available port number is found.
		</para>
		<para>
			Finally, clicking on the "Planning" tab, the windows will look like this:
		</para>
		<para>
			<figure xml:id="PWA_config_editor_planning_FIGURE">
				<info>
					<title>Configuration Editor window - Planning Tab
					</title>
				</info>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"
							fileref="resourcemanager/pics/config_editor_planning.png" format="PNG" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
		</para>
		<para> In the Planning Tab, depending on the selected connection type,
			the agent will initiate it according to a weekly planning where each
			plan specifies the connection start time as well as the working
			duration. The agent will end the connection as well as the ProActive
			Runtime process and its child processes when the plan duration has
			expired.</para>
		<para> Moreover, it is possible to specify the JVM process Priority and
			it's CPU usage limit. The behavior of the CPU usage limit works as
			follows: if the JVM process spawns other processes, they will also be
			part of the limit so that if the sum of CPU% of all processes exceeds the user limit they will be throttled to reach the given limit.
			Note that if the Priority is set to RealTime the CPU % throttling will be disabled.
		</para>

		<para>
			The "Always available" makes the agent to run permanently with a Normal Priority and Max CPU usage at 100%.
		</para>

	</section>

	<section xml:id="PWA_StartTheAgent">
		<info>
			<title>Start the agent</title>
		</info>
		<para>
			Once you have configured the agent, you can start it clicking on the "Start" button of the ProActive Agent Control window. However, before that, you have to ensure that a resource manager has been started
			on the address you specified in the agent configuration. You do not need to start a node since it is exactly the job of the agent.
		</para>
		<para>
			Once started, you may face some problems. You can realise that an error occurred by first glancing at the color of the agent tray icon. If everything goes right, it should keep the blue color. If its color changes to yellow, it means that the agent has been stopped.
			To see exactly what happened, you can look at the runtime log file located into the agent installation directory and named <emphasis role="bold">Executor&lt;runtime number&gt;Process-log.txt</emphasis>.
		</para>
		<para>
			The main troubles you may have to face are the following ones:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>You get an access denied error: this is probably due to your default java.security.policy file which cannot be found. If you want to specify another policy file, you have to add a JVM parameter
				in the agent configuration. A policy file is supplied in the scheduling directory. To use it, add the following line in the JVM parameter box of the agent configuration (<xref linkend="PWA_config_editor_general_FIGURE"/>):</para>
				<screen>-Djava.security.poly=&lt;scheduler directory&gt;/config/security.java.policy</screen>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						You get an authentication error: this is probably due to your default credentials file which cannot be found. In the "Connection" tab of the Configuration Editor (<xref linkend="PWA_config_editor_connection_FIGURE" />), you can choose the credentials file you want.
						You can select, for instance, the credentials file located at <literal>&lt;scheduler directory&gt;/config/authentication/scheduler.cred</literal> or your own credentials file.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The node seems to be well started but you cannot retrieve it in a Java code for example: in this case, make sure that the port number is the good one.
						Do not forget that the runtime port number is incremented from the initial resource manager port number.
						You can see exactly on which port your runtime has been started looking at the log file describing above.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>

	</section>
	<section xml:id="PWA_OtherInformation"><info><title>Other information</title></info>

		<para>
			The agent was successfully tested on Windows XP, 2003, Windows Vista.
			Some problems with service installation can occur on Windows NT.
		</para>

		<para>
			The ProActive Windows Agent is written in C# and uses .Net Framework 3.5
		</para>

		<para>
			Third-party libs used:
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>C# JobObjectWrapper Api (JobManagement.dll) under Microsoft Permissive License (Ms-PL) v1.1</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>C# Log4Net Api (log4net.dll - 1.2.10.0) under Apache License v2.0</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>

</chapter>
