<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="RM_API"><info><title>Use Resource Manager with Java API</title></info>
<!-- <!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V5.0//EN" "docbook.dtd">  -->

	<section xml:id="RM_API_INTRO"><info><title>Introduction</title></info>
		<para>
		Resource Manager can be used directly from the java code through its Java API. This chapter explains
		how to do that, namely how to start and stop the Resource Manager, add already deployed nodes,
		deploy nodes with GCM deployment descriptors and finally create peer to peer node source.
		Resource Manager is developed with ProActive API, so its main components are the following active objects:
		<emphasis>RMCore</emphasis>, <emphasis>RMAdmin</emphasis>, <emphasis>RMUser</emphasis>, <emphasis>RMMonitoring</emphasis> and <emphasis>NodeSources</emphasis>.
		For more information about active objects take a look at ProActive API in ProActive manual
		Part III. <emphasis> Programming With Active Objects</emphasis>.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section xml:id="RM_API_start"><info><title>Start and stop Resource Manager</title></info>
		<para>
			Resource Manager can be started locally using a static method of RMFactory class :
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java">
RMFactory.startLocal(); //creates an empty Resource Manager	</programlisting>
		<para>
		In order to perform any operations with the Resource Manager you have to authorize and
		acquire either RMAdmin or RMUser interface. This action is made by using RMConnection class :
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java">
RMAuthentication auth = RMConnection.join("rmi://my_rm_host");
RMAdmin admin = auth.logAsAdmin(username, password);</programlisting>
		<para>
		Besides RMAdmin or RMUser interfaces RMConnection allows to obtain RMMonitoring
		interface which can be used to track resources and their states.
		Once you have a reference to RMAdmin active object you can perform all administrator actions such as shutdown of the Resource Manager
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java">
admin.shutdown(true); //perform preemptive shutdown	</programlisting>
		<para>
		This method terminates all RM's active objects and stop JVM where RMCore is running. The boolean parameter that it takes
		defines whether the Resource Manager stops immediately, even there are some busy
		nodes (i.e. some nodes have been provided to an application) or waits while applications
		give them back.
		</para>			
	</section>


	<section xml:id="RM_API_GCMD"><info><title>Deploy GCM deployment descriptors</title></info>
		<para>
		RMFactory provides a way to specify a list of deployment descriptors which will be deployed once Resource Manager is started.
		Here are an example of starting the Resource Manager with 4 nodes. In this case node source with GCM infrastructure manager and
		static node acquisition policy will be created.
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java">
String gcmDeployFile = PAResourceManagerProperties.RM_HOME.getValueAsString() + File.separator + "config/deployment/Local4JVMDeployment.xml";
RMFactory.startLocal(Collections.singleton(gcmDeployFile));
		</programlisting>
		<para>
		In order to deploy nodes to existing Resource Manager RMAdmin interface should be acquired
		as in example above and then deployment can be performed
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java">
//create File object
File GCMDFile = new File("GCMDeployment.xml");
       
//put content of GCMD file in a byte array
byte[] GCMDContent = FileToBytesConverter.convertFileToByteArray(GCMDFile);
       
//launch deployment defined in GCMD
admin.addNodes(sourceName, new Object[] { GCMDContent });</programlisting>
		<para>
		Here we ask to RMAdmin to perform deployment by passing to it a byte array containing a GCMD. We can't pass
		directly the File object to RMAdmin, because RMAdmin active object can run on another JVM, a JVM different
		than JVM that executes the code above. So File is read by JVM that ask the deployment and content is transfered to RM's active object.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section xml:id="RM_API_add_node"><info><title>Add an already deployed node</title></info>
	<para>
	RMAdmin provides a way to add ProActive nodes that are already deployed, node is added with
	its node's URL.
	</para>
	<programlisting language="java">
admin.addNode("rmi://host_1/comptingNode"); //add a node identified with an URL 
	</programlisting>
	</section>
	<section xml:id="RM_API_remove_node"><info><title>Remove a node from RM</title></info>
	<para>
	You can remove a node from Resource Manager with the code :
	</para>
	<programlisting language="java">
admin.removeNode("rmi://nodeToRemove", true); 
	</programlisting>
	<para>
		First parameter is URL of the node to remove, second parameter is a boolean;
		if set to true, Resource Manager removes immediately the node, even if it is busy,
		if set to false, and node is busy, 
		Resource Manager waits that the Applications that use RM's nodes give back all the busy nodes.
		Then after removal is performed.
	</para>
	</section>
	<section xml:id="RM_API_custom_node_source"><info><title>Create custom node source</title></info>
		<para>
		You can create different node sources using admin interface of RM.
		Lets take a look at the example how to create the most complex node source.
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java">
// creating infrastructure manager parameters
Object[] imParameters = new Object[] { hostsList, GCMDeploymentData };
// creating policy parameters
Object[] policyParameters = new Object[] {
           schedulerURL, // scheduler url
           username, // scheduler user name
           password, // scheduler user password
           "true", // preemptive removal
           "0", // min modes
           "1", // max modes
           "1", // nodes per task
           "1000" // releasing period
};
admin.createNodesource("Scheduler loading node source", GCMCustomisedInfrastructure.class.getName(), imParameters,
	SchedulerLoadingPolicy.class.getName(), policyParameters);
		</programlisting>
		<para>
		Here we created the node source with GCM customized infrastructure manager and scheduler loading policy.
		In order to create the infrastructure manager we preliminary loaded host list and GCM deployment template files and transformed their
		content to bytes array. Then we defined parameters of infrastructure manager and node source policy and used
		<literal> admin.createNodesource(...)</literal> method to create new node source. It is implied that scheduler is running somewhere at the
		moment of the node source creation.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section xml:id="RM_API_user"><info><title>Use Resource Manager as a nodes provider for your application</title></info>
		<para>
		You can obviously use Resource Manager as a node provider for your distributed application. RMUser active object 
		provides a way to get and give back computing nodes :
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java">
RMAuthentication auth = RMConnection.join("rmi://my_rm_host");
RMUser user = auth.logAsUser(username, password);

NodeSet nodes = user.getAtMostNodes(new IntWrapper(4), null);

//perform some tasks on nodes provided by Resource Manager
	.
	.
	.
//and give back nodes
user.freeNodes(nodes);

// disconnecting from the resource manager
user.disconnect();
		</programlisting>
	<para>
	First we get a reference to RMUser active object, after we request a set of nodes to Resource Manager
	and perform some tasks on these nodes. Finally we give back the nodes and disconnect.
	</para>
		<para>
	Code examples above are a short overview of Resource Manager API. You can refer to Java documentation
	of Resource Manager //TODO link to RM javadoc.
	</para>
	</section>
</chapter>